<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lamentation over England from a true sight, and suffering sense, of the lamentable wickedness of such rulers, priests, and people, that are erred, and strayed from the way of God, and follow too much the devices and desires of their own hearts, offending against his holy laws ... : whereby all persecutors may (in pity to their souls) truly consider what way they are in, and whether it leads, and whose work they are doing, and what the Scripture saith will be the reward of oppression and cruelty / by M.W.</title>
            <author>Watkins, Morgan, fl. 1653-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 129 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65249</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1066</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38958</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18198593</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18198593</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107025</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65249)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107025)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1135:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Lamentation over England from a true sight, and suffering sense, of the lamentable wickedness of such rulers, priests, and people, that are erred, and strayed from the way of God, and follow too much the devices and desires of their own hearts, offending against his holy laws ... : whereby all persecutors may (in pity to their souls) truly consider what way they are in, and whether it leads, and whose work they are doing, and what the Scripture saith will be the reward of oppression and cruelty / by M.W.</title>
                  <author>Watkins, Morgan, fl. 1653-1670.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of imprint suggested by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained with some loss of print, torn; best copy available for photographing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  England --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Persecution --  England --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:107025:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:107025:1"/>
            <p>LAMENTATION OVER ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>FROM A true ſight, and ſuffering ſenſe, of the lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Wickedneſs of ſuch Rulers, Prieſts, and People, that are erred, and ſtrayed from the way of God; and follow too much the devices and deſires of their own hearts; offending againſt his holy Laws; li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting the Holy one of Iſrael; making the devices of their own hearts a Law, to inſnare the Innocent, that worſhip the Father in ſpirit and truth.</p>
            <p>Whereby all Perſecutors may (in pity to their ſouls) tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſider what way they are in, and whether it leads, and whoſe work they are doing, and what the Scripture ſaith will be the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of Oppreſſion and Cruelty.</p>
            <p>By <hi>M. W.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Evil ſhall hunt the cruel man to deſtruction.</p>
               <p>I know that the Lord will avenge the afflicted, and judg the poor.</p>
               <p>Surely the righteous ſhall praiſe thy name, and the just ſhall dwell in by preſence.
<bibl>
                     <hi>Pſalm. 140.11, 12, 13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1664.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:107025:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:107025:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Impartial Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF thy heart be upright towards God, thou canſt not but love his truth in the inward parts, which teacheth thee to ſpeak the truth, and do the truth; and to deal plainly with all men, and not to call evil good, nor good evil, nor put light for darkneſs, nor darkneſs for light; but to deal juſtly with all men, and walk humbly with thy God, and then thou needſt not fear the threats nor frowns of any man, (who is but duſt) but wilt fear the Lord, and give glory to him, (that made heaven and earth, the ſea, and the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of water) in exalting his name above every name, and his commands above the wills of men; in bowing thy heart and ſoul to the obedience of his ſpirit, that his ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting kingdome of righteouſneſs may be ſet up in thee, that the bleſsed government of his Spirit thy ſoul may be ſubject to; then thou canſt in truth ſay, the kingdom of God is come, in power, and great glory; then the Idols of gold and ſilver, and the glory of the work that periſheth, thou wilt cast to the Bats of the night, that cannot behold the Sun, and to the Moles of the earth, that know not him that gave them breath: then canst thou declare what the Lord hath wrought, and ſound forth his praiſe, to the ends of the earth; then will the voice of the good ſhepherd of Iſrael be joy to thy heart, &amp; ſtrength to thy ſinews, &amp; marrow to thy bones, and thy ſoul ſhall feed in the fat paſtures, and thy dwelling ſhall be in the hill of Gods delight, even Sion, that ſhall never be removed; into which the Father of life is ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering his own ſeed out of all Nations, Tongues, and Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, to dwell with him, in the unity of his ſpirit, and to have fellowſhip with him in his life; that his coming may
<pb facs="tcp:107025:3"/>be witneſſed in the ten thouſands of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the world, and to deſtroy the will of the fleſh, and make his great ſlaughter of all that which hath rebelled againſt him, and cannot be ſubject to the law of his ſpirit, but reſiſts, and is a law warring in the fleſh, and that nature which ſlew the Lamb from the foundation of the world, yet offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a ſacrifice, but could never pleaſe God, and they that pleaſe God, could never pleaſe it; therefore were they, and are they perſecuted, and ſuffer by it, and ſo ſpiritually overcome, and reign over it; ſo our kingdome is not of this world, but over the ſpirit of this world, neither can it be ſhaken by the powers of this world, but by its power doth ſhake the world, and ſhall over turn that foundation on which the wickedneſs is built; that the bleſsed founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Prophets and Apoſtles may be revealed before all Nations, which is Chriſt Jeſus the Light, in which the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in all nations ſhall walk; and in which, if thou that readeſt this doſt not walk, thou canſt never witneſs Gods ſalvation; but if thou believe, and in it walk, then wilt thou know this to be truth, and love to thy ſoul, from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> friend.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:107025:3"/>
            <head>A Lamentation over <hi>England,</hi> from a true ſight, and ſuffering ſenſe of the lamentable wickedneſse of ſuch Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, Prieſts, and People, that are Erred and Strayed from the way of God, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>TEnder love to all your Souls is the ſubject of this enſuing Treatiſe. And your refuſal to accept of ſo great love, as the Lord God of life holds forth to you, in this the day of his tender viſitation, is cauſe ſufficient for this my Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
            <p>Oh <hi>England, England,</hi> and ye Rulers and Magiſtrates thereof! Oh that you had priſed this the day of your viſitation! Oh that you had hearkened to the voice of the truth, in the mouths of the Prophets and ſervants of God, who have finiſhed their faithful teſtimony (ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of them) with the laying down of their lives! And that you had not deſpiſed (and ſtill do deſpiſe) and perſecute, thoſe whom he hath ſent unto you! Oh that the blood of his pretious ſervants did not lie at your doores, which cries loud for vengeance in the ears of the juſt God of heaven and earth, till he make Inquiſition for it! How many have been impriſoned till death, for obeying the will of God? And how hath their blood been mingled with their ſacrifices, when they have been peaceably met together in the fear of the Lord, and in the dread of his power, out of the fear of him that kills the body? but in the love and patient nature of the Lamb that overcomes the wrath and ſaves the ſoul, who is the higheſt power that the ſoul ought to be ſubject to, who hath given it life, breath and being, and who can caſt it into Hell fire if it obey him not.</p>
            <p>And therefore you are very much miſtaken in us, who think to frighten us out of our Religion (by perſecution or killing the body) it being that which the Lord hath raiſed up in us by his mighty pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, in the denyal of our own wills, and ſo contrary to all mens wills that have not ſubmitted to his power: For when he appeared in his power, to place his fear in our hearts, then our fleſh trembled, and <hi>Immortality was brought to light through the Goſpel,</hi> which was the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:107025:4"/>voice of the Son of God to our ſouls, by which we came to hear and live; which life is contrary, and which voice is dreadful to the fleſh, and <hi>ſo we having felt the terrors of the Lord for ſin and tranſgreſſion,</hi> do not at all fear the terrors of men, <hi>which can but kill the body, and when that is done, can do no more.</hi> Therefore, friends, you knew not what you did, when you began to meddle with us, and make laws a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, and perſecute us becauſe we could not ſubmit to your wills; for had you known us, you would not have begun ſuch an ill work, wherein you ſhould have loſt ſo much labour, and gained ſo much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour, and alſo incurr'd the wrath of God.</p>
            <p>Had <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> known the <hi>three Children</hi> as well before as he did after, he would never have forced them to worſhip his golden Image; but after he came to know them, <hi>be loved them, and honoured them in the ſight of his Nobles, Princes, Dukes, and Counſellors,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing them to be the <hi>ſervants of the high God;</hi> commending their faithfulneſſe in yielding their bodies (to the flames) rather then they would ſerve or worſhip any God, <hi>ſave their own God.</hi> Then he ſaw his vain labour in forcing the ſervants of the moſt high God, contrary to the commands of their God.</p>
            <p>And will you ſhew your ſelves more unreaſonable then a Heathen, more blinder then thoſe that knew not God? (and yet call your ſelves Chriſtians, and the Scriptures your Rule.) When <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> had once tryed the <hi>three children of God,</hi> to the laying down of their lives, and found them faithful, he was ſatisfied. How many times have you tryed us, by Impriſonment till death, and ſpoyling of our goods, by breaking up our Meetings, beating innocent harmleſſe people to death? How many Cruel, Barbarous, Unhumane dealings have been uſed againſt us (both before your Government, and alſo ſince by you) which we have walked through, and in the <hi>furnace of affliction, with the patience of the Son of God,</hi> who hath kept our precious lives unhurt, and brings us forth to his praiſe? and yet cannot you ſee the Son of God with us (whom you fight againſt)? Can you not ſee neither, how little you do prevail againſt him, and his ſpiritual work in us? Though ſome of you can ſay, We are a very confident people, but if you could but ſee him that leads us <hi>(who is the Captain of our ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion)</hi> you would ſay, We had good cauſe to be <hi>bold and valiant,</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our leader is not to be overcome, nor thoſe that follow him, <hi>who are called, and choſen, and faithful;</hi> which faithfulneſſe <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:107025:4"/>did commend and honour. And did he not do well in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> (Yes) you cannot deny: Then as you have followed his example, by indeavouring to compel us to fall down to your imaginary worſhip, (which I believe you will not juſtifie in him) follow his example alſo in juſtifying <hi>the faithful children of God,</hi> that would not obey his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, to the diſhonouring of the <hi>moſt high God;</hi> who having tryed them, bleſſed God for their faithfulneſſe. In this will <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar</hi> ſtand in Judgment againſt all thoſe, who make <hi>unrighteous Decrees</hi> to compel men to diſobey the commands of Chriſt, except they follow his example in this, that is to ſay, the change of their minds, and altering of their <hi>Decrees,</hi> in Juſtifying the <hi>faithful ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God</hi> in their pure obedience to him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Objection.</hi> But if it be ſaid, If we knew you to be <hi>the ſervants of the high God,</hi> as well as <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> knew the <hi>three children,</hi> we would not make Laws nor Decrees to compel you to our worſhip, being ſure it would be but loſt labour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Then all our ſufferings, and perſecutions, and hard uſages from you, is becauſe you do not know us; and whoſe fault is that, ours or yours, that you do not know us to be the <hi>children of God?</hi> Whoſe fault was it that <hi>Saul</hi> the perſecutor knew not the <hi>Church of God,</hi> but made <hi>havock</hi> of the true worſhippers, were they to be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med or he? If he, then you; when he hearkened to the <hi>High Prieſts,</hi> he perſecuted the Diſciples of <hi>Jeſus;</hi> but when he obeyed the voice of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> he ſaw their deceit, and believed the <hi>truth;</hi> then he preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, and ſuffered with thoſe he perſecuted. Now if you (that perſecute) knew the <hi>truth,</hi> you would know us that walk in it. And have not we laboured, even to the laying down of our lives, that you might know it, and be ſaved by it? What could we have done more for you then we have, to bring you to the knowledg of it? Have we not ſuffered to the death, in obedience to it, that it might preach to you, that we have found <hi>the kingdom of heaven, and the righteouſneſs thereof</hi> (which is better then our lives) <hi>for which righteouſneſs ſake we ſuffer, and are bleſſed,</hi> if we continue faithful to the end.</p>
            <p>And this is the only true way that can be uſed as to you, to convince your underſtandings that we are in the <hi>truth,</hi> when we lay down our lives for it. If we were unfaithful to our God, and diſobedient to his Spirit, in obeying your commands, that are contrary to the <hi>truth,</hi> you had no reaſon to judge or think we were in the <hi>truth;</hi> for had the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:107025:5"/>
               <hi>three children</hi> been deceitful, and obeyed the <hi>Kings command,</hi> he had never knew them to be <hi>the ſervants of the high God,</hi> that was able to deliver out of his hand. And the deliverance that he ſaw, was of their bodies from the flames, that made him bleſſe the God of their lives; but the deliverance that we witneſſe, is of our ſouls from ete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel death, which is far greater, and more glorious, yet you cannot ſee it; but if your ſpiritual eyes were open, as his fleſhly eyes was, then you might ſee a greater deliverance in the ſpirit, then he ſaw in the fleſh; and would have as great or greater cauſe, to bleſſe the God of thoſe you in ſcorn call <hi>Quakers,</hi> as the King <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> had to bleſſe the God of <hi>Shadrach, Meſhach,</hi> and <hi>Abednego,</hi> though he be the ſame <hi>God over all, bleſſed for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet his appearance in this <hi>the great and notable day of the Spirit,</hi> is that in which the riches of his love [is] and ſhall be made manifeſt, which was promiſed to the ages to come, which now is come, of which the Apoſtles and Diſciples of Chriſt were the firſt-fruits; but now is the day of the whole Harveſt of the earth begun, in which the Lord is gathering in unto himſelf, his Elect ſeed in all Nations, Lands and Countries, even from the one end of the earth unto the other, that they may worſhip in ſpirit and in truth, and be eſtabliſhed in righteouſneſſe, <hi>and the Mountain of the houſe of the Lord be prepared, in the top of the mountains, and be exalted above the hills, where all Nations ſhall flow unto it; out of which ſhall go forth the Law, and the word of the Lord from [this] Jeruſalem; and they ſhall break their Swords into Plough-ſhares,</hi> (Mark, the day of the breaking of Swords is begun) <hi>and their Spears into Pruning-books, and Nation ſhall not lift up ſword againſt Nation, neither learn to fight any more.</hi> And this is the day that is dawned, and bleſſed are they that walk in it, but wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and miſerable are all thoſe that deſpiſe it, and perſecute thoſe that walk in the light of it, caſting them into Priſons, Holes, and Dunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, becauſe they cannot ſubmit to their corrupt wils, nor worſhip the Imaginations of their Wiſe men, which they teach for Doctrine, and give forth for a Preſcription of a Religious Worſhip, contrary to the practice of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, whoſe Worſhip ſtood in the Spirit. But, I believe, if all you that reſiſt us knew in what our Worſhip did ſtand, you durſt not oppoſe that power that hath gathered us, and made our ſouls ſubject, knowing thereby you ſhould reap Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:107025:5"/>
            <p>But we know the power that is able to deliver us out of your hands, and will deliver us in his time (which is not earthly but heavenly) into the hands of which power we have given up our ſelves, and therefore are not careful what ſhall become of our mortal bodies, that the will of God may be done, and <hi>the trial of our faith</hi> appear to his glory, <hi>who hath called us out of darkneſs into his marvellous light;</hi> in which we are to ſtand, <hi>and bear all things, and ſuffer all things, that we may overcome all things that oppoſe themſelves againſt the truth;</hi> for that which is againſt the truth is againſt God, and God is againſt it, and all that are acted by it, and in it, I am ſure they cannot proſper.</p>
            <p>And friends, this is my lamentation over you; Oh! that you had not choſen that which cannot proſper; Can I do any leſs than mourn over you? and can I do any more for you, than warn you (in the tender bowels of love to your ſouls) and walk out of that which I warn you to depart from, and ſo ſtand a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for God againſt it; for the which, I, and many others ſuffer, and are perſecuted and hated becauſe we tell you the truth; even that which God hath manifeſted to us, and brought us into, which comes contrary to your wills, therefore you cannot hear us: but if your wills were ſubjected to the truth in your ſelves, then the ſingle eye would be open in you, <hi>and the whole body would be full of Light,</hi> then you would ſee that in your ſelves which is contrary to God, and alſo that which is one with him; and that which is contrary being caſt out in your ſelves, you could not own it in others wherever you ſaw it; and this is it that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrains us to declare againſt that in others, (out of love to their ſouls) which God hath condemned, and caſt out of us; whereby we come to be witneſſes of his power, and that <hi>he is come that doth deſtroy the works of the Devil,</hi> and brings forth his own work in us, and daily perfects it, through ſufferings and trials, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the oppoſition of the Devil; for the more it is oppoſed, the more it ſhall proſper, and the more it is perſecuted, the more it ſhall increaſe, becauſe it is the work of God, and for the glory of his great and powerful name; he is engaged to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate his own work he hath begun in and among us, and we know he will do it, and never leave us nor forſake us.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:107025:6"/>
            <p>For he hath been better to us already, than our natural lives, who hath raiſed up in us a meaſure of his own ſpiritual life, which we cannot but give obedience to, though it be to the loſs of the natural: but alas for you! can nothing ſatisfie you but our deſtruction? becauſe our lives are not ſquared by your wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, muſt we therefore loſe them? becauſe we cannot run with others, into the ſame exceſs of riot, muſt we not therefore live in the moderation? becauſe our liberty ſtands not in the fleſh, muſt we therefore be impriſoned? becauſe we cannot meet in Taverns and Alehouſes, to be drunk, whore, and blaſpheme the name of God, muſt we not therefore meet to ſpeak good of his name? becauſe we cannot maintain and uphold a changeable, time ſerving Prieſthood, with our eſtates, muſt we therefore loſe them? becauſe we cannot diſobey the Lord, to obey man, therefore muſt we be baniſhed out of the land of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity?</p>
            <p>Alas for you! Is this your Juſtice and Judgment to your own Country men and Neighbours? what will it be to ſtrangers? is this your liberty for tender Conſciences? or is this to <hi>do as you would be done by?</hi> is this your learned Biſhops and Doctors Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine for a ſoul cure, to impriſon, and kill the body? be not theſe the weapons of your Lords ſpiritual, or your ſpiritual wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons? in what do they differ from the inſtruments of a fooliſh ſhepherd; (it is clear, as the Scriptures of truth do teſtifie) theſe are not the Inſtruments of the true and wiſe Biſhop, and ſhepherd of our ſouls; theſe weapons and inſtruments the Apoſtles and Biſhops of our Lord Chriſt did never uſe; but on the contrary, theſe were uſed againſt them, by the unbelieving high Prieſts, and perſecuting Rulers of the Jews, and by the wicked, heathen Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates that knew not God.</p>
            <p>Alas, poor blind men! how do you ſhew your nakedneſs, and yet are not aſhamed? Do you think the old covering will hide you now? no, it is worn too thin and too narrow; a thin co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering would ſerve in the night, but now the day is dawned in our hearts, the light is riſen, and your covering is ſeen through; the children of the light ſee you, therefore you hate and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute them, and ſo ſhew forth your Wolviſh nature, which is to deſtroy, and not to ſave; for the way of ſalvation you perſecute,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:107025:6"/>and are ſtrangers to the meek nature, and the ſheep of Chriſt will not hear nor follow ſtrangers; becauſe they (alone) know them, that they cannot lead in the way they are ignorant of, and ſtrangers to: and therefore we turn from you, and that Church which is not in God, but are, as you ſay, a company of miſerable ſinners, all polluted and ſpotted with the Leproſie of fin and tranſgreſſion; and, as you ſay, there is no health in you; and have we not good cauſe to deny that Church, in which there is no ſaving health? but have erred, and are ſtrayed from the way of God like loſt ſheep; and ſo your Members are found living in ſwearing, and curſing, and lying, drunkenneſs and whoredom, and all manner of notorious wickedneſs, for the which many are yearly put to death as Milefactors; and what a great matter you make of it, for to proceed againſt us to excommunication, when you know that we have denied, and ſeparated from your Church (of miſerable finners) long ago; for the ſheep of Chriſt cannot follow ſtrangers, that are erred and ſtrayed from the way, in whom there is health; but the bleſſed and glorious Father of life hath revealed in us his ſaving health, and we witneſs his living power, and bleſſed preſence, that hath, and doth ſave us to the uttermoſt; and there is health and ſoundneſs among us, bleſſed be his glorious name for ever, who hath gathered us according to his promiſe, out of the mouths of the falſe ſhepherds, and from among thoſe that are erred and ſtrayed from the good ſhepherd, and Biſhop of their ſouls, who being from the way, are loſt, and without they return muſt periſh: ſo knowing that as you are ſtrangers to the life, and the way, ſo alſo are you to the weapons of the Chriſtian warfare, which are <hi>ſpiritual;</hi> (ſo are not yours) <hi>and mighty to the pulling down the ſtrong holds of the Devil;</hi> (ſo are not yours) which many thouſands are witneſſes of; glory be to the <hi>great ſhepherd, and biſhop of our ſouls, for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And alſo, have we not good reaſon to turn from you, when you turn from Chriſt, <hi>the true Light, that gives the true knowledge of the glory of God, in the face of Jeſns Chriſt,</hi> 2 Cor. 4.6. For the want of obedience to the which Light, you come to erre and ſtray from the way of God, and are (as you ſay) in the loſt ſtate, like loſt ſheep; and no marvel, when you will not hearken to the voice of the true ſhepherd, and biſhop of the ſoul, and they which
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:107025:7"/>do, you perſecute; and ſo will not receive the knowledge of the truth your ſelves, and enter into the kingdome, nor ſuffer thoſe that would, as much as lieth in you; you ſhut the kingdome of heaven againſt men, as did the chief Prieſts, and Scribes, and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees of old; therefore woe is to you, that ever you were born: alas for you! how will you be able to ſtand in the dreadful, ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible day of Gods righteous judgment, that is coming, and ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily haſtens upon you, who are found oppoſers of the work of the ſpirit of truth; even that ſpirit that the Apoſtles and Diſciples of Chriſt were Miniſters of, that is it <hi>that leads into all truth,</hi> into which the good ſhepherd is gathering his ſheep, wherein is wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed the perfect gift, that leads out of ſin and imperfection, the gift of the ſpirit of faith, that overcomes the ſpirit of the world, that leads into bondage, and ſo come to witneſs <hi>the glorious liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the ſons of God,</hi> 2 Cor. 4, 13.3, 17. (which is in the ſpirit) for where the ſpirit of the Lord is, (received) there is liberty: from what? from the bondage of ſin and corruption, (not in ſin, and the luſts of the fleſh, as many would have it) but in the ſpirit, that leads out of ſin, and mortifies the luſts of the fleſh, as the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Walk in the ſpirit, and ye ſhall not fulfill the luſt of the fleſh,</hi> Galat. 5.16. which you Prieſts cannot believe, though the Scripture ſaith it; you are not come to the ſpirit of faith that overcomes the world, who ſay, we can never be free from ſin while we are upon earth; hath not he dominion over ſin, that doth not fulfill the luſts of the fleſh? as it is written, <hi>Galat.</hi> 5.24. <hi>they that are Chriſt, have crncified</hi> (mark) <hi>the fleſh, with the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and luſts;</hi> theſe that are Chriſts did witneſs a victory over ſin, who lived and walked in the ſpirit, and <hi>the law of the ſpirit of life in Chriſts Jeſus, made them free from the law of ſin and death;</hi> Mark, theſe were ſuch that walked in the ſpirit and were the ſons of God, who ceaſed from ſin; for it is written <hi>John</hi> 8.34. <hi>he that committeth ſin is the ſervant of ſin;</hi> that is not one of the ſons of God, that is made free indeed; <hi>for know ye not, that to whom ye yield your ſelves ſervants to obey, his ſervants ye are to whom ye obey, whether of ſin unto death, or of obedience unto righteouſneſs; for when ye were the ſervants of ſin,</hi> (mark before Chriſts words, that is, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſin) <hi>ye were free from righteouſneſs, but now being made free from ſin, and become ſervants to God, ye have your fruit unto holineſs,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:107025:7"/>and the end everlaſting life.</hi> Rom. 6, 16, 20, 22. then there was a freedome from ſin in the Apoſtles dayes, as they bear teſtimony in the ſpirit of God; and we who believe their teſtimony, and are come to the ſame ſpirit, and cannot but bear the ſame teſtimony, according to our meaſure, receiving him in the ſame ſpirit of faith, do receive the ſame power to become <hi>the ſons of God.</hi> Now ſeeing there was a freedome from ſin in the Apoſtles time, who witneſſed his glorious appearance to <hi>put away ſin,</hi> and that he had done in them the work he came into the world to do, that is, <hi>to deſtroy the works of the Devil;</hi> how comes it to paſs now that this Doctrine of the Apoſtles can find no more place in this generation of prieſts and people? it is becauſe <hi>they love darkneſs more than light,</hi> and their luſts and evil deeds, more than the life of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; and ſo would perſwade the people, that there is no ſuch life of righteouſneſs to be brought forth here on earth, as the Apoſtles ſpake of and witneſſed, and the Scriptures bear teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to; ſo it doth clearly appear what kingdome you are of, and whoſe ſervants you are, <hi>that cannot ceaſe from ſin, beguiling unſtable ſoules</hi> (mark) theſe the Apoſtle ſaith are the falſe teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, <hi>that being in damnable hereſies, who through Covetouſneſs and feigned words, make merchandiſe of you;</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2, 14.2, 1.3. who walk after the fleſh, in the luſt of uncleanneſs, <hi>that cannot ceaſe from ſin;</hi> (mark) but plead for it terme of life; theſe are they that beguile the unſtable, and ſtrayed ſheep; <hi>whoſe hearts are exerciſed with covetous practiſes; curſed children, which have forſaken the right way, and are gone aſtray,</hi> (like loſt ſheep) <hi>following the way of</hi> Balaam <hi>the ſon of</hi> Bozor, <hi>who loved the wages of unrighteouſneſs; to whom the miſt of darkneſs is reſerved for ever,</hi> becauſe they hate the light, <hi>and love darkneſs more than light,</hi> it juſtly becomes their portion.</p>
            <p>And who is he that will be ſo wicked, as to ſay we ought not to turn from theſe, who prove themſelves to be in the way of <hi>Balaam,</hi> both in life and Doctrine, a company of miſerable ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, <hi>that cannot ceaſe from ſin, being erred and strayed from the right way,</hi> that leads out of ſin? therefore bring another Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine to plead for it, and turning the Doctrine of truth into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meaning, to uphold your contrary practice, and cover your life, that the Apoſtle bare teſtimony againſt whoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:107025:8"/>was from <hi>the gift of the ſpirit of truth,</hi> which ſaith, <hi>every good giving, and every perfect gift is from above, and cometh down from the father of lights,</hi> James 1.17. and as many as come to this good and perfect gift, receive it, and are taught by it, are led into the <hi>good old way</hi> of truth and righteouſneſs; which is the perfect leadings of the perfect ſpirit of God into his perfect life, by which the command of God comes to be kept, which ſaith, <hi>Be ye there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore perfect, as your Father which is in heaven is perfect;</hi> Matth. 5.4, 8. and the Apoſtles ſaid, <hi>they kept his commands, and did that which was right in his ſight,</hi> but you, prieſts and people, that are erred and ſtrayed from the good and perfect way, cannot keep his commands, nor do that which is right in his ſight: for it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible you ſhould, till you come to the good &amp; perfect gift of God, and becauſe it is impoſſible with you, you think it is ſo with all; but that which is impoſſible with you, is poſſible with God; and all who do receive him, the perfect gift of Gods power, and walk in it, are come to witneſs the dominion of the ſon of God, which is over ſin, hell, and death, and ſo becomes the ſons of God, <hi>that can do nothing againſt the truth, but for the truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you that call your ſelves Miniſters of Chriſt, that have not received the perfect gift of God, that cometh from above, which is for the perfecting of the Saints, you are not ſent of God, and cannot profit the people at all, and are but intruders into that you underſtand nor, and cannot do the Lords work, but are making a trade of felling the Apoſtles words, and Chriſts words, and the Prophets words, being ignorant of the word of faith, in the heart, and in the mouth, which they preached; which is the Goſpel, that is hid to thoſe that are loſt, and gone aſtray, by erring from the way of life, which the Miniſter of Chriſt is to turn the people to: that is, <hi>from the darkneſſe to the light,</hi> (which you that God never ſent, hate, and ſay it is natural) and <hi>from the power of Sathan, unto God;</hi> which you that have not received the gift of God, cannot believe is able to deſtroy the works of the Devil, while you live upon the earth, ſo you are wholly igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the power of the kingdome of God that is come; (and will conſume the Antichriſtian) wherein, the will of God is done in earth (mark that) as in heaven; and this you pray for, yet believe againſt: or elſe you muſt believe, it is the will of God,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:107025:8"/>that men ſhould live in ſin, as long as they are on the earth: but the Apoſtle ſaith the contrary, in theſe words, <hi>this is the will of God, even your ſanctification;</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.3. and they who are come to the gift of the ſpirit that ſanctifies, cannot but bear teſtimony to the ſalvation of God, <hi>through ſanctification of the ſpirit, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the truth,</hi> 2.13. but you that have received your gift from your fountains of <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge,</hi> which are beneath, and cometh from the corrupt nature, that ſtands in the fall and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, eſtranged from the Covenant of life, erred and ſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the right way, (which is the gift of the ſpirit) and are in the way of fallen nature, and its gifts; and theſe gifts can never lead out of the fall up to God, becauſe they are but from beneath, and cannot bring to the knowledge of God, nor his truth; for <hi>Pilate</hi> had the natural gift of Tongues, as <hi>Latin, Greek,</hi> and <hi>Hebrew,</hi> and by it he could not know the truth, but ſaid to Chriſt, what is truth? <hi>John</hi> 18.38. ſo you that have received your gift from beneath, knows not the mind of the ſpirit, which is the mind of Chriſt (which the Apoſtles by the ſpirit had) but you ſtudy to make a meſſage of your own, according to your own mind and imagination; and when it is made, you muſt have money for it, becauſe you came not by this art of Sermon-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king without money: and although you ſhould be but bunglets at this trade, and not maſters of this art, yet if you can get a ſhop and ſet up, the people muſt be compelled to pay you, though they abhor your work; and this makes your trade ſo much in requeſt, (and truth ſo much perſecuted:) but muſt we buy your imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, becauſe you bought your art? this is not equal nor juſt, nor ever ordained of God, as his Ordinance; yet we ſubmit our ſelves, in ſuffering patiently, till the Lord take off this oppreſſion, and break this yoke. Was it ever heard of in any age, that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were compelled to buy chaff to eat, when they might have wheat for nothing? had not the Prodigal more liberty among the ſwine, than we have among ſuch as accout themſelves ſheep of Chriſt? for he might eat the husks freely, though it ſatisfied not his ſoul, till he returned to the fathers houſe, where he had bread enough freely: and we who are come to the Fathers houſe, and have bread ſufficient, <hi>cannot ſpend our money for that which is not bread, and our labour for that which periſheth;</hi> but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:107025:9"/>to exhort all to ſeed upon the bread that is living, <hi>that comes down from heaven, and giveth life unto the world: Joh.</hi> 6.33. and this is the gift the Father of life hath given, and bleſſed are all they that do receive it.</p>
            <p>But from your fountains of <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge</hi> doth flow forth a ſpirit of perſecution, and ſtrife againſt the truth, as we by ſad experience have felt, and witneſſed for theſe ſeveral years, whereby many of us have loſt our lives, by long impriſonment and cruel uſage, which that ſpirit hath occaſioned, by ſtirring up the people, and Magiſtrates, to fulfill their wills: and if we ſhould ſay this ſpirit were of God, we ſhould lye againſt the truth; <hi>but this is the wiſdome that deſcendeth not from above, but is earthly, ſenſual, and devilliſh:</hi> this cometh not down from above, and therefore it oppoſeth that which doth.</p>
            <p>For the Doctrine of the Apoſtles of truth is this, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.10. <hi>Let every man as he hath received the gift, miniſter the ſame one to another,</hi> (not for money but) <hi>as good diſpoſers, or ſtuards, of the manifold grace of God.</hi> Now if any who have received the good and perfect gift of God, that cometh down from the Father of Lights, in obedience to the ſpirit of truth, goes to communicate of his gift to others, then he is counted an offender, by that ſpirit which came from <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and the Lords of that ſpirit and Prieſthood have made a Law againſt it; even againſt that which the Lord Jeſus doth command, by his eternal ſpirit in his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, which they, and his Diſciples did practice, and muſt pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, notwithſtanding all oppoſition. Can you be ſo ignorant as to think your law ſhall bind his ſpirit, from miniſtring in whom, and where he pleaſeth? Can you ſtop the Sun, that it may not go its courſe? If not, conſider what will become of them that ſtrive againſt their maker, and the work of his eternal ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Do you think, that he that hath received the gift of miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from above, will be ſtopped by your Law, which is from beneath? If you meaſure that ſpirit, with the wiſdome from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath, you may think ſo, but we have received another ſpirit, than that of <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge;</hi> for that ſpirit hath been ſtopped by the commands of men, becauſe its commiſſion is but from man, ſo man commands them to be ſilent, and they are ſo;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:107025:9"/>becauſe they be the Miniſtry of the powers of the Nation, who gives them their Wages; ſo the National Miniſtry are but the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the National power, as it doth appear; for vvhen the powers changed, the Miniſtry changed, except they turn vvith the time, as for the moſt part they do, and lick up their own vomit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, as it is clear to moſt people they have done of late. How did they cry out againſt the Common-prayer ſome years ago, to be ſuch an abominable thing, as not fit to come into their mouths? but now, rather then loſe a fat Benefice, they can ſwallow it down Surplice and all. Doth it not appear now who preach for money? We told you ſo many years ago what you ſhould find them; but now you ſee it your ſelves, who they be that make no conſcience what they ſwallow, (they ſwallowed ſo much trebble damage in <hi>Oliver</hi>'s days) that their throat is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as an open ſepulchre, and are in that ſpirit of covetouſneſſe (that the Prophet ſaid) never hath enough; which is ſo greedy, that having one or two Pariſhes, yet labours to have more; and ſome are ſo unreaſonable, to require Wages for ſome years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they came to the place, which, it may be, ſtood vacant ſo long, yet they can ſwallow that Hire, though they never did the Work. So the light hath made manifeſt their deeds of darkneſſe, the hidden things that vvere in the heart (being now come to be tryed and brought forth) ſo the evil covetous man, out of the evil treaſure of his heart, hath brought forth the evil things, and the tree comes to be known by its fruit. Now I ſay theſe things only to thoſe that be guilty of them; but to you that ſay our prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>I ſay, Did you not change your practice, and conceal your prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple and practice is the ſame that it vvas before the former chang, ciple? Did you nos Conform to the Commands of thoſe you counted not of God? Did you Preach, and hold forth your gift of Miniſtration (notwithſtanding the Law and Commands of men) till you vvere Impriſon'd? If you had received your gift from above, and your Commiſſion from Chriſt, you would have choſe rather to have obeyed God then man: (as the Apoſtles did, and Miniſters of Chriſt do) for had the Prophets, and Apoſtles, and ſervants of God in former ages, obeyed the powers of the earth Actually, their Laws vvould have protected them, that they could not have ſuffered Perſecution, and Impriſonment, and Death
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:107025:10"/>as they did: But the National Law did ever protect the National Prophets, vvhich, for the moſt part, vvere ever falſe, as the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures do bear teſtimony.</p>
            <p>But it is the Lambs Nature that doth overcome (which you perſecute) which preacheth and ſhews forth its perfect love through ſufferings; and if you were in this nature, and we in error as you ſay, then you would ſhew forth a life beyond ours, which is the life of truth, that keeps the commands of God, which life dwelleth in love, and if we were in hatred it might overcome us; but on the contrary, we being in the ſuffering life of Chriſt and his Apoſtles and Diſciples (who never perſecuted, nor ever will) and you in the life that perſecutes, it is given to the ſuffering life to overcome you, and that ſpirit by which you are acted (and this is the word of the Spirit of Truth, that ſhall ſtand over your heads for ever.) But by that ſpirit, and thoſe weapons, it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to overcome us, who ſtand in the obedience of the ſpirit of truth, (mark that) becauſe <hi>our ſtrength is the power of God,</hi> and while we believe in it, it can never fail us nor forſake us: We know him to be the Corner ſtone, who is tried, Elect and precious; and the higheſt of you all ſhall know, that he in whom we have believed in, is higher then you all, to fave and deliver us when he hath ſufficiently proved and tryed us; and therefore you may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of the fooliſhneſſe of thoſe Inſtruments and Weapons you uſe, which the former Power of Profeſſing Hypocrites uſed againſt us, before you: And what did it profit them, who perſecuted that life they did profeſſe in words? and would not be warned, till the Lord heard the cry of the Innocent, and aroſe and took their power from them (who had abuſed it) and gave it unto you, and muſt you needs follow their ſteps (whom you condemn and ſo much deſpiſe) and abuſe the power you are intruſted with, which is, <hi>to incourage him that obeys the truth, and to puniſh him that obeys unrighteouſneſſe.</hi> And do not you Magiſtrates the contrary? thoſe that meet together in the fear of the Lord, and worſhip in the meaſure of his holy ſpirit, do not you hale forth, break up their Meetings, and carry them to Priſons, and by your Law condemn to be baniſhed? But thoſe that meet together in Taverns and Ale-houſes, who ſwear, drink till they be drunk, and whore, to the great diſhonour of God, and the Government of the Nation,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:107025:10"/>yet theſe can be let alone in their wicked meetings, and go unpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, when Honeſt, Innocent, Harmleſs people are fined and ſent to priſon.</p>
            <p>What can you ſay to this? Is not this an abuſing the power put into your hands to do good withal? or do you think the end and intent of Gods Ordinance is, to puniſh his people for obeying his command? If not, why is it done? For as ſure as Magiſtracy is Gods Ordinance, ſo ſure are we his people, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for well doing: Then, If this be ſo, you muſt confeſſe we are abuſed and ſuffer innocently, though many of you will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it, for if you did, then we ſhould not ſuffer: For ever yet, in all Ages, Perſecutors were blind; therefore, as in a figure, the ſcales ſell from <hi>Sauls</hi> eyes, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.18. <hi>For had the Princes of this world known it,</hi> (that is, the miſtery of godlineſſe) <hi>they would not have crucyfied the Lord of glory,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.8. But though you cannot ſee the miſtery of our life, yet you may ſee the open prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that is daily ſuffered to be acted in this Nation, and that can go unpuniſhed. Why? becauſe ſome that ſhould puniſh it, may be guilty of the ſame things themſelves; this miſtery of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity is not hid from your eyes; yet your ſword is not a terror to this; is it not then born in vain? Me thinks you might ſee to bit ſome of the wickedneſſe at a venture, it is plentiful enough ſprung up, and eaſie to be found, far eafier than a meeting of harmleſſe, innocent people that fear the Lord, and deſire to live peaceably in the Nation; but ſuch many of you will take great pains to ſearch you, and go beyond the Letter of the Law to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh: And if we were forward to take the advantage of the Law upon ſome of you, all you had would hardly ſatisfie what the Law gives for ſatisfaction. But we have committed our innocent cauſe to the Juſt God of heaven and earth, and we do aſſuredly know (that except you repent, and that ſpeedily) he will give you weight for weight, and meaſure for meaſure, becauſe he is Juſt, <hi>and will not alwayes ſuffer the rod of the wicked to remain upon the back of the righteous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And how comes it to paſſe, that your ſword falls upon our backs ſo much? I am ſure its not for diſhonouring God by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe, for if we did ſo, then we might be ſafe enough from the danger of it, and we ſhould have friends in every place (but
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:107025:11"/>in the heavenly place in Chriſt Jeſus) whereas we now have ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies in moſt places: And why ſo? becauſe Magiſtrates, Prieſts, and people do the things they ought not to do; and in this I muſt needs ſay, You ſpeak the truth in the preſence of God: but if you had done the things ye left undone, and ought to have done, then you had as well done the truth, as ſpoke the truth: then you might have brought your deeds to the light (with bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) and it would have been made manifeſt that they were wrought in God, whereas now you muſt needs confeſs that which leads you to do the things you about not to do, is the ſpirit of the Devil, that is againſt the truth, and leads to perſecute it; but the Lord is cur witneſs, that the deſire of our ſouls is, that you might come to that ſpirit that leads to do the things you ought to do, which is the ſpirit that leads into all truth; then you and we ſhould not differ, but ſhould be one Church in God, and one people that are bleſſed for ever, and till you come here, we ſhall alwayes differ from you, (though never fight with you) both in life and Doctrine; <hi>for they that do not the will, ſhall not know the Doctrine;</hi> but if we, or any of us ſhould be ſo wicked, as to turn from the ſpirit of truth, and do the things which we ought not to do, and leave the things undone which we ought to do, then we ſhould come to you, and be of your Church, which is not in God, and then woe will be to us that ever we were born; and then indeed we might fight, drink, and whore, and ſwear, and curſe, and then we ſhould be counted good ſubjects to the King, but I am ſure we ſhould be better to the Devil; but the Kings beſt ſubjects indeed are they that <hi>fear God, who depart from evil,</hi> theſe honour the King, and the King will in a little while know theſe to be his beſt friends, who cannot flatter him for their own ends, <hi>and have mens perſons in admiration for advantage;</hi> but when their earthly ends is not anſwered, they can turn againſt him for a better advantage; for hath not money cauſed many to betray their truſt? and oaths will not bind where God is not feared but where he is: <hi>they muſt render to Ceſar the things that are Ceſars, and to God, the things that are Gods:</hi> for they that are Gods people, do only know the things that are Gods, that only belong to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and they cannot give to <hi>Ceſar</hi> the things that are Gods, for that were evil, and unjuſt before God, and out of his
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:107025:11"/>fear; and therefore they that are not in his fear, do quarrel with us about thoſe things, who would have us to give <hi>Ceſar</hi> all; that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not do, but the things that are his we freely give: <hi>Tribute to whom tribute is due, Cuſtome to whom Cuſtome, fear to whom fear, honour to whom honour,</hi> Rom. 13.7. Now all this doth not belong to <hi>Ceſar,</hi> for fear belongs to God, and therefore we cannot give all to <hi>Ceſar;</hi> Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute and Cuſtome we give, and in that, with the obedience to all his Juſt commands, we honour him: And in that which for Conſcience ſake we cannot do, we patiently ſuffer, and ſo we do <hi>ſubmit to every ordinance of man for the Lords ſake,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.13. But it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>Fear God, and keep his Commandements, for this is the whole duty of a man,</hi> Eccleſ. 12.13. So our duty is, to render to God his due, that is, <hi>to keep his commands, and do that which is right in his ſight.</hi> And when <hi>Ceſar</hi> commands us to do that which God forbids, then <hi>we chuſe rather to obey God then man;</hi> and ſo we ſhew forth that we fear him <hi>that is able to deſtroy both ſoul and body,</hi> if we do not obey him: So in the things that belong to our ſouls, we are to hear the heavenly voice, of the Biſhop and Shephard of our ſouls, <hi>becauſe every one of us ſhall give account of himſelf to God,</hi> Rom. 14.12. And it is juſt and Gods due, that the ſoul ſhould be ſubject to that power that hath given it life, breath, and being, that is; <hi>the higher powers the ſoul ought to be ſubject to, the powers that be, are ordained of God,</hi> Rom. 13.14 To be Miniſters of God for good (and not for evil) but if the Miniſters of the power (given for good) turn the power againſt the good, they are not Miniſters for God; for God hath not ordained the power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the good: So he that is againſt the good, is againſt the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God, and God is againſt them that abuſe the power or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for good, and he will avenge and execute wrath upon them that do evil.</p>
            <p>Thus it is clear, Rulers (for God) are not a terror to good works, but to evil; and it is as clear, that they which ſeek to terrifie thoſe that do that which is good, are not Rulers for God; and ſo do not fear him, nor honour the King, for it is written, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.3. <hi>He that ruleth over men muſt be juſt</hi> (mark that) <hi>ruling in the fear of God;</hi> and he that ruleth in his fear, cannot puniſh thoſe that meet in his Name, and keep his commands, becauſe they do the things they ought to do; but they that rule not in Gods fear, are not juſt in puniſhing thoſe that keep his commands, and in doing that which they ought
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:107025:12"/>not to do; theſe ought not to rule over men, <hi>who fear not God, nor honour the Kings</hi> to ſuch I ſay, doth God (do you think) love curſing, and ſwearing, better then a ſilent waiting upon him in his fear? if you think not, why do you puniſh the one, and let the other alone? or is the Law againſt the fear of God, and not againſt the profaneneſs, becauſe it is executed upon the one, and not upon the other? and think ye that God loveth profane ſongs, and wicked talk, before or better then a good exhortation, from the Spirit of truth, that people might keep Gods holy will and commandments, and walk in the ſame all the dayes of their lives? how can you expect to proſper that do theſe things, who tread in the ſteps of thoſe, whom God overthrew before you? did they accompliſh their end in perſecuting of us; did they cauſe us to come to their worſhip, or ſubmit to their wills, or did they ſcatter and overcome us? did not the Lord ſcatter and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them, who roſe up againſt his work in us? and how do you think to eſcape, doing the ſame things as againſt us, who are a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that would lay down our lives, that your ſouls might be ſaved, in this the day of the Lords viſitation?</p>
            <p>But alas, alas for you, you have ſlighted the day of Gods love to your ſouls, and your miſery is, you cannot believe it, but when it is too late to return you may feel it; and then you ſhall confeſſe we were your beſt friends, who told you the truth, though you hated us for it; yet the reward of our love to you, we ſhall receive at the hand of the Lord, and you the reward of your hatred and cruelty towards us (its the word of the ſpirit of truth to you all) for we are a people that have done you no wrong at all, and as we walk in the truth, we do profeſſe and own we cannot wrong you, nor any upon the face of the whole earth; but you have wronged us, and do daily, in afflicting, puniſhing and perſecuting us, as evil doers, and as a people not fit to live upon the earth; but know this from the Lord that lives for ever, what you have deſigned againſt us in your hearts; ſhall be your own portion, becauſe we are of the ſeed of the ſpiritual Jews, whoſe Kingdom ſhall flouriſh for ever.</p>
            <p>But what is the evil, and what is our crime, that we are thus reckoned as ſheep for the ſlaughter? is it not only, becauſe we cannot break the commands of God, and his ſon Jeſus, and own your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which he never commanded, nor his Apoſtles and Diſciples ever practiſed; but warned thoſe that feared God, to depart from them
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:107025:12"/>
               <hi>that were lovers of pleaſures, more then lovers of God, covetous proud, unholy men, deſpiſers of thoſe that are good, walkers in their own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly luſts, ſpeaking great ſwelling words, having mens perſons in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration becauſe of advantage, who run greedily after the error of</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam <hi>for reward,</hi> (and to cover all this) <hi>hold forth a form of godlineſs, but denying the power thereof, from ſuch turn away,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle of Jeſus Chriſt, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. and becauſe we do ſo, therefore are we hated, and perſecuted, but if we could <hi>put into your mouths,</hi> then we might ſave the ſpoyling of our goods, and be accounted good Chriſtians, though we ſerved the devil; but we are come to the knowledge of the truth, (everlaſting praiſes be given to our God for ever and ever) and to the power of godlineſſe, that cannot bow nor creep to deceit, but muſt bear teſtimony <hi>(with the holy Prophets and Apoſtles, and the bleſſed company of Saints and martyrs of Jeſus)</hi> againſt preaching for hire, and divining for mony, and ſpoyling mens goods, for trebble damages, caſting their bodies into priſons till death, and all for mony and for gain from their <hi>quarter:</hi> Oh blood thirſty, bloody minded men, deſtroyers of ſouls and bodies, for your bellies; who never have enough: woe, woe from the Lord is your portion, that ever you were born, to live to exceed the falſe prophets of old, and yet profeſſe Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>For we do not read, that ever they did force any by ſuite of Law to pay them; but we read, that <hi>Balaam,</hi> when he did not his work that he laboured ſo mightily to do for the King of <hi>Moab)</hi> which was to curſe the people whom God had bleſſed; (mark) when he could not do his work, he went away without his reward; and ſo is it not meet that thoſe, whom in this nation are ſent by men, (pretending authority over ſouls) and put into Pariſhes and places, to reform and bleſſe the people; and cannot do their work, but the people grow worſe and worſe, though they take pains (yet God never ſent them) and is it reaſon that they ſhould have ſuch a great reward, as the tenth of all our labours? <hi>If they had ſowen ſpirituals, it had been a ſmall thing for them to have partaked of our carnals; or if they had planted a vineyard, they ought to have eat of the fruit thereof:</hi> But this Vineyard of Times the Pope hath planted for his Prieſts, and never intended it for theſe, who do not his work, nor the Lords neither.</p>
            <p>And therefore, why may not they, with <hi>Balaam,</hi> return without a
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:107025:13"/>reward from the King, ſeeing their bleſſing doth as little good, as <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laams</hi> intended curſing did harme? for he went away without the Kings great honour and promotion, becauſe the Lord would not ſuffer him to fulfil or ſatisfie the will of that ſpirit, which would have had the Iſrael of God deſtroyed, <hi>Num.</hi> 24.11. <hi>but ſo</hi> (ſaith the King) <hi>the Lord ſhall keep thee back from honour:</hi> But wo be to that ſpirit that willeth the deſtruction of Gods Iſrael now, that it may keep or get its earthly ends, and ſelfiſh fleſhly honours, which God is riſen in his mighty power to bring into contempt, becauſe it oppoſeth it ſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the work of his ſpirit, <hi>which is to bring down the earthly, and exalt the heavenly:</hi> Which work muſt and ſhall be done, when men and devils have don, and ſaid what they can; for he that made us for his praiſe, hath now by his ſpirit quickened us up again for his glory. <hi>And this is the Lord from heaven, that ſpirit, that as is the heavenly, ſuch they may be that are heavenly:</hi> That the heavenly Image may be exalted above the earthly, both to rule and reign over it in the Lambs patient nature, to overcome the earthly, which preacheth forth to the heavenly Witneſſe in all conſciences: <hi>So the long ſuffering and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, leads to repentance and newneſs of life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that ſpirit which turneth people from the gift of God in them, is the deceiver that ſtrengtheneth the hands of the evil doer, to make War againſt the appearance of God (in man) that brings ſalvation: and this is the falſe Prophet that hath and doth deceive the Nations; which ſecond appearance of Chriſt <hi>(the true ſpiritual light) is to conſume with the breth of his mouth, and the brightneſſe of his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this appearance of truth, <hi>in the inward parts,</hi> the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet cannot endure: [Mark,] becauſe it is come to <hi>reveal and conſume him;</hi> and therefore he thinks to ſtrengthen himſelf by the powers of the earth, in perſwading them to believe his report and Prophecy, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſpirit of truth; and they being not come to the word of life in themſelves (that was before the deceiver was) do not diſcerne him, and ſo come to be deceived by him, and to make War againſt the brightneſſe of the riſing of the Son of righteouſneſſe, and the lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of his pure ſpirit of life in his Children, by making Laws and Decrees againſt them, for the exerciſe of their pure Conſciences to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God and man: <hi>And hear is the tryal of their faith made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to be precious,</hi> by which many comes to be added to it, and the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:107025:13"/>kingdom exalted by its own power, through oppoſition and perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo it comes to be ſeen and known to be the power of life in us, that is greater and mightier then the power of death and darkneſſe that comes againſt us, that we can of a truth ſay, <hi>He that is in us, is greater then he that is in the world,</hi> who comes againſt us, but muſt be overcome by him that is in us, whoſe power ſhall burſt the bonds of wickedneſs, &amp; deſtroy the ſpirit of perſecution, that makes Laws for ſtumbling-blocks to the people that have a deſire to ſeek after the Lord, and come to the meaſure of his ſpirit, that leads into all truth; that they may witneſſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over ſin and the works of the Devil deſtroyed in them, and they forſake him, and all his works, and all the vain pomp of this wicked world (that both Prieſts and People live in) with the filthy unclean luſts of the fleſh, that they may keep Gods holy will and Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (that the Prieſts and people, for the moſt part, ſay they can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver keep here) and walk in the ſame all the dayes of their lives: and if this ought to be done, as you ſay; and is poſſible to be done by the power of God, as I ſay, then let the Prieſts bring forth one out of all the Pariſhes in <hi>England,</hi> that they by their miniſtry have taught and brought into this perfect life, which they have made the people pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe and vow, that the Children ſhall perform when they come to age.</p>
            <p>Now if they have, and ſtill do make the people promiſe and vow, That the Children ſhall do that which all the Prieſts in <hi>England</hi> cannot do, then in all juſt reaſon the people ſhould have the Tithes; but if the people do not performe this vow, and bring forth this life, and the Prieſts and Biſhops to help them, then what is all your Religion worth, that have not God a bridle for your tongues, that promiſe and break it, that vow ſolemnly before the Lord, and not perform it? You may very well ſay, you are a generation of miſerable offenders, and there is none of you doth good (as it doth appear) no, not one: And yet you Prieſts would have a reward for teaching the people to profit, when you cannot bring one of all your Flock that hath done that which you ſay (and they promiſe and vow) they ought to do. Firſt you ought to do your Work, before you require your Wages; but you take the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward firſt: ſo you are herein more cunning then <hi>Balaam,</hi> for you are ſure of the reward, though you never do the work; and moſt of you are not aſhamed to ſay, it can never be done here, yet you ſtill take the Wages. Can this be any other than the wages of unrighteouſneſs?
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:107025:14"/>to be paid for deceiving the people, keeping them <hi>ever learning, and never able to bring them to the knowledge of the truth,</hi> but ever would be paid, though never do the work; therefore you are unprofitable ſervants, and no Miniſters of Chriſt, and therefore we cannot follow you, who deny the light of Chriſt within, and ſo you chooſe the darkneſs, for that will not reprove you for your unprofitable works, and they which walk there cannot ſee your deceit: therefore you love the darkneſſe more than the light, and the wages of unrighteouſneſſe more than the truth, which is the perfect gift of God, given to profit withall: and this is the reaſon you cannot profit the people, becauſe you have not received the perfect gift of God, that the Apoſtles and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt did receive (and do receive) which was given <hi>for the perfecting of the Saints, for the edifying of the body of Chriſt;</hi> and they I believe ſpake truth, when it was ſaid by <hi>Paul,</hi> that he ſpake wiſdome among thoſe that were perfect; <hi>and that they that were ſanctified were perfected for ever,</hi> and the Scripture bears teſtimony of ſome that were ſanctified.</p>
            <p>So theſe could ſhew the fruits of their Miniſtry, that they did perform that, which they received the gift of God to do; theſe did not receive the tenths of mens labours, yet they did their work, but you receive the tenth, and ſay the work can never be done here: if the work be to be done in another world, what have you to do to take wages here? but indeed you are like to have none of us in this world, except you can do your work in this world: but the Apoſtles and Miniſters of Chriſt, through the power of their gift, brought men to the keeping of the commands of Chriſt, who ſaid, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.48. <hi>Be ye therefore perfect, as your Father in heaven is perfect:</hi> (and you prieſts make the people vow and promiſe to perform) and is it not his will, that this command ſhould be kept on this ſide the grave? if not, why do you make the people promiſe to do it? for he that forſakes the Devil and all his works, and keeps Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly will and commandments, ſhews forth, and witneſſeth a perfect life.</p>
            <p>But if you have taught the people to promiſe and vow that which they, nor you, can never perform, then you have led the people into errour; and if it be not errour, then you are er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:107025:14"/>from the ſpirit, the gift of God, by which the people ſhould be perfected, and the body of Chriſt edified, being that your Miniſtry hath brought forth no ſuch fruit, and its like never will.</p>
            <p>Therefore conſider with your ſelves, what cauſe thoſe that love your ſouls have to warn you, and deal plainly with you, that if it be poſſible you may ſee your error, and come to that ſpirit that leads into all truth; for its not poſſible for you to cover your ſelves, but the eye which God hath opened in the children of Light, doth ſee you, and the woful, ſad, miſerable, lamentable eſtate that you are in; woe, woe unto you, weep and howl for the miſery that is coming upon you: what an account can you give to the Lord for all the ſouls that have periſhed under your cure? who have not made (with all your wiſdome and skill) one ſoul perfectly whole, but ſtill have laboured to keep them ever learning, where they can never be able to come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the truth. Woe, woe unto you, that ever you were born, to be an occaſion of ſuch a great deſtruction, in underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that which you have no ſpiritual skill in; had you received the word of Life from the Lord, <hi>the word would have healed them,</hi> ſo there would have been ſome fruit to God: if ſome had pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, who had refuſed to hear, or have been inſtructed by you, you might have been clear of their bloud: but the people have heard you, and do hear you, and if they come not, you puniſh them: and yet alas! all ſpotted with Leprofie, and there is (as you, and they ſay) no foundneſs in you, but all over polluted with wounds and putrified ſores: are not you judged out of your own mouths, by your own confeſſion before the people? and then to cover your ſhame and errour, you make the people believe, it is not ever poſſible to be otherwiſe here. Oh miſerable comforters to a ſick ſoul! If the people did but ſee your deceit, what would become of you? but the Lord God of Life is making your deceit manifeſt daily, (by the light which you hate) and all the children of Light ſee it, who are taught by his ſpirit, and therefore cannot but pity your poor miſerable ſouls. Alas! what will you do, when none ſhall buy your Medicine any more? how will you look the people in the face, in that day which haſtens ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly for <hi>Sions</hi> ſake? you muſt ſly to the rocks &amp; the mountains
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:107025:15"/>to cover you, but they ſhall not be able: <hi>for the mountains ſhall tremble in that day, and the hills ſhall melt before the Lord, and the glory of his power that is riſen, and ariſing to ſhake terribly the earth,</hi> and bring every hidden thing to the light to be tryed, and that which cannot ſtand in the Light, ſhall be caſt into the lake of fire, which is the ſecond death.</p>
            <p>Now again conſider with your ſelves, you that ſay the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers (as you call them) are in error and deluſion, and perſecute them as hereticks; was not that alwayes the ſaying of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors? ſee the teſtimony of the Scriptures: was it not alwayes ſo ſaid by them that were born after the fleſh, whoſe wills they have made a law, and ſo were never without a law to kill the juſt: and if that they had be not bad enough, then the old envious nature can make another that ſhall be, which law did ever uphold the unjuſt, and pleaſe the falſe Prophets and hirelings, becauſe they would not have their deeds brought to the light, and themſelves made manifeſt to be in darkneſſe: but after all your cruelty and perſecution againſt us, what caſe will you be in, when the Lord doth appear for us openly, and vindicate our innocent cauſe, by his juſt Judgments upon all our enemies, in making them exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of his wrath to all generations, that the people that are afar off may hear, and dread, and fear to reſiſt his mighty power, that is riſen, and ariſing to ſhake all Nations, <hi>and ſhall bring down the haughtineſſe, and the loſtineſſe of man, and ſtain the glory of all fleſh, and bring all the honourable of the earth into contempt,</hi> that the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, immortal, heavenly ſeed of life, may be exalted over all; <hi>and the kingdomes of the world become the kingdomes of the Lord, and of his Chriſt, whoſe right it is to reign, and rule over all, bleſſed for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wo unto you Rulers in darkneſſe, Magiſtrates in <hi>Sodom,</hi> and Governours in <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> for the terrible day that is overtaking you, and you would not be warned: how oft hath the Lord ſent unto you by his meſſengers and miniſters of truth, both by ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and writing, that you might be gathered out of that ſpirit which leads to deſtruction, <hi>but you have ſet at naught all his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, and would none of his reproof, therefore ſhall you eat the fruit of your own way, and be filled with your cruel devices: for your life in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſhall ſlay you, and your proſperity in fooliſhneſſe ſhall deſtroy you,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:107025:15"/>becauſe ye have hated the knowledge of the truth, and would not chooſe the fear of the Lord;</hi> therefore ſhall fear come upon you in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and deſtruction as a whirlwind, then will your wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and cruelty againſt the ſervants of the Lord, be ſet in order before you, who have required them evil for good, and for their labour and pains to bring you into the <hi>glorious liberty,</hi> you have put them into priſon, oh! this will be heavy upon you, when their bloud comes to be required at your hands, who ſhould have employed your power to have encouraged them in the ſervice of the Lord, which is the well doing; and ſo ſhould you have had praiſe of God and all juſt men, and your memorial would have been ſweet in generations to come: but on the contrary, your memorial will rot, and your name be blotted out from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heaven; but the memorial of the juſt (whom you perſecute) ſhall flouriſh for ever.</p>
            <p>Wo, wo be unto you ſpiritual Lords (ſo called) that decree un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous decrees, to bear rule over the conſciences of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and Lord it over Gods heritage, who labour to devour the flock of Chriſt, and lay waſte his little remnant, that he hath ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered to bear teſtimony to his great and glorious name, that he is exalting over all Nations; and becauſe you have combined againſt him, and the great and glorious work he hath begun in this Nation, his power is turned againſt you, and ſhall purſue you in all your wayes, and defeat you in all your deviſes, till he hath left you neither root nor branch, and your name ſhall be caſt out as an abominable thing, and an abhorring to all people; for you have exceeded the blaſphemy of thoſe who ſaid they were Jews, and were not, in calling your ſelves Fathers in God, and yet never came to witneſſe the ſpiritual birth of the children of God, <hi>who are come to know their ſins forgiven them, for his name ſake,</hi> into which they are gathered, where the Father comes to be known, by the revelation of the ſon, that is life eternal: <hi>and hereby we do know that we know him, if we keep his Commandments;</hi> 1 Joh. 2.3. this was, and is the ſaying of the children of God, which you, Fathers in God (as you are called) never came to witneſſe; to wit, the keeping of the Commandements of Chriſt: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you that do believe his Commands, cannot be kept while you live on the earth, in that unbelief you are ſhut out, and there
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:107025:16"/>can never come to know him, and he that is there, and ſaith he knows him, is a lyar: 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.10. <hi>In this the children of God are manifeſt, and the children of the Devil; whoſoever doth not righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe is not of God, neither he that loveth not his brother.</hi> In this the Fathers and Children that are perſecutors (for conſcience ſake towards God) are manifeſted to be of their father the Devil, and neither children nor fathers in God.</p>
            <p>For the name Father in God came from ſuch as were in that nature, who were firſt <hi>children of God that had known the Father, and then young men that had overcome the wicked one, then fathers becauſe they have known him that is from the beginning,</hi> 1 John 2. 13 14. and in the power of God that was in the beginning, that doth overcome, did beget unto God, and ſo were properly and truly called Fathers in God; and ſuch I own, and honour in my very ſoul, who are honourable in the houſe of God, <hi>and as they ruled well, were worthy of double honour,</hi> from all the children of truth in the Fathers houſe, but had nothing to do with thoſe that were without, that were not of the houſhold of faith, for the Devil bare rule there in the children of diſobedience: and, ſaith <hi>Paul, them that are without, God judgeth; for what have I to do to judge them alſo that are without?</hi> 1 Cor. 5.12, 13. The Biſhops and Fathers in God, did rule only among the children of God, who were the Church in God, and they that abode in Chriſt were his Members: 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.6. <hi>And he that ſaith he abideth in him, ought himſelf alſo to walk even as he walked;</hi> who ſaid, <hi>I receive not honour from men:</hi> (that is, ſuch who will not come unto him, cannot honour him, but in the unbelief diſhonour him) but he that believer, <hi>poſſeſſeth his veſſel in ſanctification and honour;</hi> (that is to him that ſanctifieth:) but the Fathers in God, and Biſhops of Chriſt, never took upon them the vain glorious ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of the wicked world, nor were called maſters or Lords, but were hated of the world, as their Lord and Maſter was, (and ſo ſuch are now) that the Scripture may be fulfilled, for ſuch are not of the world, but of God: for, ſaid they, <hi>the whole world lyeth in wickedneſſe,</hi> and they were with ſound Doctrine, and a holy Converſation, to beget unto God, out of the world, and if you, who are called Lords ſpiritual, did exerciſe your au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority over none, but they that you had begotten to God out of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:107025:16"/>the world, you would have but a very ſmall flock, if any at all; but inſtead of gathering a flock out of the world, you take the world for your flock, and ſo exerciſe Lordſhip over them; (as Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.25. <hi>The kings of the Gentiles exerciſe Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip over them,</hi> the example of thoſe you follow, and not Chriſt:) for there is many thouſands by the year to be gotten by them, and ſo rule by your outward power and Lordlineſſe (like the falſe Prophets of old) and many of the world love to have it ſo: and ſo let them have it. But the flock of Chriſt, <hi>the Church in God,</hi> cannot own theſe things, nor love to have it ſo, but muſt ſtand witneſſes againſt theſe things, even to the death, if the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire them.</p>
            <p>And therein you come to be tried, and made manifeſt what nature you are of, and alſo their faith and patience is made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, and the nature of the Lamb ſhewed forth, that overcomes: but the contrary nature (as I have ſaid) is to be overcome; that which perſecutes, and impriſons, and would force the conſcience, and ſo ſlay the ſoul, or elſe kill the body, this was ever of the Devil, (and ſo it is now) and a mark of Antichriſt, the falſe Church, the Whore, that is adulterated from the Spirit, and alienated from the Lambs nature, that overcomes in patience, and obtains the victory, <hi>and is made perfect through ſuffering;</hi> but on the contrary, the Whore, the falſe Church, is ſaid <hi>to drink the blood of the Saints;</hi> and the Scripture bears teſtimony, that all the bloud is ſound in <hi>Babylon,</hi> (then <hi>Sion</hi> is clear of bloud.) Mark that, and the name <hi>Babylon</hi> comes thus to be written in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of every perſecutor, who is of <hi>Cains</hi> ſtock that ſlew his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe his worſhip was in truth, but his in the murthering nature. (Mark) he that was ſlain was in the truth from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and he that ſlew was in the deceit; and ſo we ſee it hath been all along unto this very day.</p>
            <p>And that nature which ſlew our Lord Chriſt, when he was up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth, is the ſame that now perſecutes, and ſlayes his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and followers, <hi>becauſe they are redeemed from the earth,</hi> and cannot ſubmit to their vain traditions, cuſtomes, and faſhions, and commands, that are contrary to God, therefore are ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers by the world; <hi>but the ſons of Sion are ſuch, who are redeemed with judgment,</hi> and that nature which is at enmity to God being
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:107025:17"/>condemned, is crucified and caſt out, and the Lambs nature be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing raiſed up, converts to righteouſneſſe, and righteouſneſſe being brought forth, glorifies God.</p>
            <p>And we, being called and gathered <hi>cut of the vain converſation,</hi> and alſo from the vain worſhip, <hi>(which teacheth for Doctrine the commands and traditions of men)</hi> by the mighty power, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtretched arm of God, are kept in faithfulneſſe to him, that we cannot bow, or ſubmit to that which the Lord hath ſhewed us to be evil, for fear of men, or their threats, who are but duſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accompanied in our ſufferings and perſecutions, with the power and preſence of the eternal God, that made heaven and earth.</p>
            <p>And be it known unto you (perſecutors of the holy ſeed) you ſhall never prevail to overcome us, as we are kept in the power of Life, which hath gathered us out of your dead forms, to ſerve the God of Life in the newneſs of his ſpirit, in which he is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped by the true worſhippers, out of the way, ſight, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of all that are not come to receive the true light, who are all in a falſe worſhip, erred from the ſpirit, blind, in the dark, and ſtumble at the truth, and fight againſt the life, <hi>that is hid with Chriſt in God, out of the ſight of the vulterous eye, and out of the way of the venomous beaſt, where the lions whelp treads not, and where the devourer cannot come;</hi> and that which God hath hid in the ſpirit, all the natural learning in the world could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver find out, nor ever ſhall; for being hid from the wiſe and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of this world, is revealed to ſuch as are babes, who hunger and thirſt after righteouſneſs, (and not after preferment in the world) who cannot be ſatisfied with the bread that periſheth, <hi>but with the ſincere milk of the word of life they grow, which word is nigh them, and is the word of faith in their hearts,</hi> that begets life in them, and this life pints and breaths after nouriſhment, from that which hath begotten it, and cannot be ſatisfied with words, but with the immortal word of life that was in the beginning, that quickeneth that again, that in <hi>Adam</hi> we were dead to; and this is the quickning ſpirit that miniſters life, which we having obeyed, do live; <hi>and the life we now live is by the mighty power of God,</hi> which our ſouls are made ſubject to, and we cannot but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey that which quickned us, and is the immortal life in us the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:107025:17"/>ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> that the children of the firſt perſecute, becauſe they are born of that which cannot reveal the ſecond, and ſo being in the darkneſſe of death, ſee him not nor know him.</p>
            <p>But alas for you! it is in vain for you to think that you can prevail over us by your carnal weapon, for the ſword of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is with us, which hath ſlain and cut down that nature in us, that your ſtrength ſtands in, to make War againſt us: for the ſtrong man, the enemy of our ſouls, being overcome (by the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of life that is ſtronger) comes to be caſt out, who is the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that leads all perſecutors, and all deſtroyers of mens lives for Conſcience ſake; that is, he that would deſtroy us, being caſt out from within, and cannot deſtroy our ſouls, would revenge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf upon our bodies; (but we know that he that hath given life to our ſouls, can preſerve our bodies if he pleaſe, if not, his will be done) but this I ſay to all perſecuters, We have overcome your Captain-general, <hi>and he that is in us, is greater then he that is in the world</hi> (as we have ſaid, and you ſhall know) <hi>who is the Captain of our ſalvation,</hi> that ſuffered by the world, and overcome the world; and therefore know this, that as our Captain hath overcome the world in us, ſo with us, and in us, will he overcome the world by us; (but this the world ſeeth not, therefore cannot receive it). ſo if all the world riſe up againſt us, as one man, for the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the ſpirit of truth, we know it is, that they may be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome.</p>
            <p>And how can you expect that we ſhould ſubmit to that in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which God in his dreadful power did condemn, caſt out, and deſtroy in us? But while we did ſubmit to it in our ſelves, then we could ſubmit to it in others: for when death reigned, deceit was honourable; but when life came, death was deſtroyed, deceit denyed, truth exalted, and God honoured, and our ſouls ſaved; and ſo in Gods ſalvation we ſtanding, Men and Devile cannot prevail againſt us.</p>
            <p>Now if you perſecutors could believe this, then you would know it were in vain to ſtrive againſt us, for in ſo doing you ſtrive againſt the Lord, and muſt needs reap deſtruction; but on the contrary, if we did not know theſe things brought forth in us, by the mighty power of God, then we might believe it were in vain to reſiſt your wills, and ſuffer the loſſe of our lives, goods, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:107025:18"/>not knowing for what. For what would it profit us to ſuffer for that which could not ſave and deliver our ſouls from eternal death? When we were in deceit, we could not ſuffer for the truth, becauſe the truth did ſuffer by us, and in us, but now coming into the truth, deceit is denyed and caſt out into the world, and there rageth at us in all deceivers; who are deceived that think to ſtop the way of the Lord, and the work of his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in <hi>England; Therefore we chuſe to ſuffer with the truth, being ſure we ſhall reign with the truth</hi> (over all that is againſt it) for that power that hath, and doth free us from the enemy within, in his due time will deliver us from the enemy without, <hi>and from the hands of all that hate us, that we may ſerve him, without ſear of them, in righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe before him, without controul of men, all the dayes of our lives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore Infallibly knowing our ſelves to be led and acted by the ſpirit of the Lord God, in the obedience of his will, we do alſo know as well, that all our enemies who oppoſe, perſecute and oppreſſe us, except they repent, ſhall all be deſtroyed and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh eternally: and therefore how can we but pity your conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, pray and mourn for you in ſecret, that if it be poſſible, you may <hi>come to the truth and be ſaved,</hi> before it be too late, and then we can neither pray nor mourn for you, when you have ſealed your deſtruction with our blood, it will be too late for you? (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you have had ſuch warning before-hand from the ſpirit of the Lord in his ſervants) then the voice of our blood (which is pretious in the ſight of the God of heaven) will cry loud for ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance againſt you: <hi>How long, holy and true, before thou aveng our blood? doſt thou not judge and avenge our blood on them that dwell on the earth?</hi> Rev. 6.10.</p>
            <p>Woe, woe, from the Lord God of power, to all blood-thirſty Rulers, Judges, and Magiſtrates, who hunt after blood, perſecute and condemn the innocent who doth not reſiſt you: in you is the reſurrection of the unjuſt and cruel muthering ſpirit, which is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen and alive to fill up the meaſure of iniquity and cruelty; to bring to remembrance before the Lord, all the bloud that hath been ſhed in your great City <hi>Babylon;</hi> and woe for ever will be to thoſe that are found acting in that murthering ſpirit, <hi>for upon that ſpirit will the Lord render vengeance in flaming fire, for all the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:107025:18"/>blood that hath been ſhed upon the earth.</hi> And the woful, dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, terrible day of your deſtruction (who are in that nature) draweth nigh, wherein you muſt ſuffer puniſhment for every evil thought, and wicked word and action againſt the innocent (who ſuffer for the obedience of his will) as done unto himſelf, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.6. <hi>In as much as ye have done it unto one of the leaſt of theſe my brethren, ye have done it unto me:</hi> And again, ved. 10. <hi>But who ſo ſhall offend one of theſe little ones, which believe in me,</hi> (mark) <hi>it were better for him that a milſtone were hanged about his neck, and that he were drowned in the depth of the ſea: And take heed that ye deſpiſe not one of theſe little ones,</hi> who cannot Bow to mens Inventions and Traditions, ſet up in the wills of ſome men, and pulled down in the wills of other men; but we are come to the ſtanding wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in the Will, Power, and Spirit of God that abides for ever, which men and devils ſhall not prevail againſt: though ſome may ſtretch forth their hands to vex certain of the Church, as <hi>Herod</hi> did, <hi>Acts</hi> 12.1. becauſe he ſaw it pleaſed their [enemies] the Jews, but it pleaſed the Lord to make an example of him, and he was eaten with worms, that it might be a warning to all ſelf-conceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ambitious, proud, highminded, perſecuting Rulers and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates in the ages to come.</p>
            <p>And if (<hi>Depart from me ye curſed into everlaſting fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels, Mat.</hi> 25.41.) be the portion of thoſe that do not viſit the little ones, his brethren in priſons, and dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons, and naſty holes where they are caſt, for the teſtimony of his truth, what ſhall be the reward and portion of thoſe that caſt them in, and throng them together, to the deſtruction of their lives for want of freſh aire, that they may be murthered in ſecret, without Judgment or Mercy? but alaſs for you! the cry of their innocent bloud will find you out (both actors and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters) and bring you to open Judgement for your ſecret wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe.</p>
            <p>And if God do not openly appear in terrible Judgment againſt you for theſe things, then you may ſay, Tuſh, God ſeeth it not; or that he hath forſaken the earth, or that he is not mindful of thoſe that diligently ſeek him: but we know; and you ſhall aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly know, <hi>you have touched his annointed ones, and offended his lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ones, and deſpiſed them, ſlain his Prophets, and done deſpight unto
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:107025:19"/>his ſpirit of grace.</hi> Therefore vvoe is me for you, vvhat vvill you do in that day (that is nigh at hand)? Who ſhall deliver you from the ſtroke of his vengeance? Who ſhall ſave you from his fierce wrath? Alas, alas! Who can utter the miſery, or declare the terrible Judgments that is to come upon <hi>Babylon,</hi> and all her Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, and perſecuting Rulers and Governors that are found alive in her ſin when God ſhall render vengeance for all the bloud that is found in her, and they in the bloud? Woe upon woe, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery upon miſery, plague upon plague is coming upon thee, <hi>O Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, thou mother of Harlots, and abomination of the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh happy are you, ye Inhabitants of <hi>Sion!</hi> bleſſed, yea for ever bleſſed be the day, in which that love was manifeſſed to your ſouls, that hath gathered and brought you out of the City of confuſion, <hi>Miſtery Babylon the great:</hi> Though you may loſe your, mortal lives for a teſtimony againſt her, yet you have cauſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce for ever, that you are made worthy <hi>to follow the Lamb, and fill up the meaſure of his ſufferings, and ſo receive an exceeding weight of glory, which is laid up for all thoſe that continue faithful to the end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Woe, woe from the Lord is the portion of all that oppreſſe <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> and that ſpoil <hi>Iſrael;</hi> who exerciſe rule and authority over the bleſſed ſeed, in the curſed nature; and ſo being Gentiles by nature, are ignorant of the Laws Statutes and Ordinances of <hi>Sions</hi> King, and of his ſpiritual <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who are of the heavenly birth that is bleſſed, and cannot bow to <hi>Eſau</hi>'s Lordſhip, who is of the firſt birth that is hated, which cannot pleaſe God (being in the unbelief and under the curſe) and yet doth exerciſe autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and oppreſſe the birth that doth: (Mark) <hi>He that is in the fleſh cannot pleaſe God,</hi> thus ſaith the Scripture, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.29. And he that perſecutes is of that birth, as it is written, <hi>He that was born after the fleſh, perſecuted him that was born after the ſpirit.</hi> Even ſo it is now; (then mark) how can that birth that pleaſeth God ſubmit to that birth which pleaſeth him not? It could not do ſo of old both in the Prophets and Apoſtles, it cannot do ſo now in Diſciples and Believers: and becauſe it cannot do ſo now, the birth of the fleſh would force them, by inflicting puniſhment upon their bodies, and ſpoiling of their goods; but he that gave them bodies is a Spirit, and gives them ſpiritual power to overcome
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:107025:19"/>that ſpirit of darkneſſe, in giving up their bodies, that they may not bring guilt upon their ſouls.</p>
            <p>And from this birth that cannot pleaſe God, doth the enmity ariſe in all ages; from the firſt that was <hi>Cain,</hi> to the laſt that is <hi>Antichriſt.</hi> For the ſeed that bruiſeth the heele, rules in that birth that perſecutes in all ages, and is but one, though it change its name, yet its nature is to devour and deſtroy the life, in which the ſeed rules that is bleſſed; <hi>which is the Heir that the ſons of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lial in all ages have combined to kill,</hi> under the name of a deceiver or a blaſphemer; for old <hi>Cains</hi> Nature having put on Chriſte Name, <hi>profeſſeth him in Words, but denyeth him in Works,</hi> as ſaith the Scriptures by its teſtimony under the ſeveral appearances and diſpenſations of God, it alwayes, and in all ages teſtified againſt that nature.</p>
            <p>For as in the time of the Law, old <hi>Cain</hi> covered himſelf with a profeſſion of it, and with the ſtricteſt, would <hi>Tithe Mint and Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min (but neglected the weightier, Judgment and Mercy.)</hi> And when the Heir appeared in a body of fleſh, to do his Fathers will (mark) he could not own <hi>Cains</hi> Religion, although he profeſt his fathers Law: Then the old enmity ſaid, Come let us kill him, this is the Heir; but what ſaith the old enmity now in our age? Come let us make a Law to Baniſh them, to ſpoil their goods, and hang them as Fellons, and what not? is the old enmity grown worſe, that it rages ſo much? it knows who is appeared in his mighty power, and that its time is but ſhort; for the Heir is again ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, and appearing in the bodies of his people to do his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers will, and theſe cannot own <hi>Cains</hi> Religion now, no more then their Lord Chriſt owned it then; for the Heir of life know <hi>Cains</hi> nature then (and ſo he doth now) notwithſtanding his taking the Law of God into his mouth, yet he was from it in his heart (for there was the murtherer in the heart, where the Law ſhould have been) ſo the Heir of life, <hi>the light of the world, that manifeſts the deeds of darkneſs now,</hi> ſaid then, <hi>to thoſe Rabbies that went in long robes, and for a pretence made long prayers, yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured the poor, Woe be to you hypocrites, for ye ſhut up the kingdome of Heaven against men; for you neither go in your ſelves, neither ſuffer ye them that are entring, to go in,</hi> Mat h. 23.13. (Mark how the old enmity wrought then) he that came to do the will of God they
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:107025:20"/>killed; for having told them before that their Religion was vain, <hi>and that they were of their father the Devil, and his works they did,</hi> yet they believed not, but perſecuted to the death; ſo deſpiſed the day of their viſitation, and him that told them the truth, both hated and ſlew.</p>
            <p>Therefore <hi>was their houſe left unto them deſolate, and the things that belonged to their everlaſting peace was hid from their eyes.</hi> So it being ſea for an example in the following ages, that perſecution is puniſhed with deſolation; and that ſpirit that ſeeks not after truth and peace with all men, the peace of God is hid from its eyes, and that is the fugative and vagabond ſpirit that ſlew his brother becauſe he pleaſed God; and this is that ſpirit that reigns and rules in great <hi>Babylon, that drinks the blood of the Saints and Martyrs of Jeſus;</hi> and this is the ſpirit that is Head in the falſe Church, or Scarlet coloured Whore, that calls her ſelfe the Spouſe of Chriſt, and covers her ſelf with his Name, being erred from his ſpirit, dwels in enmity to his nature; <hi>this is that ſpirit of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt that is come into the world, with which the great men of the earth have been led to commit fornication with,</hi> and drawn their hearts from the meaſure of his good ſpirit in them, which would have guided their feet into the way of peace: but that ſpirit of enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty being received, guids their feet into the way of <hi>Cain,</hi> to kill and ſlay their brother that cannot ſacrifice with them, nor own their Worſhip in that nature which cannot pleaſe God; and for this cauſe have the holy men of God ſuffered in all ages, as at this preſent day.</p>
            <p>And becauſe of this our Lord Chriſt ſuffered, who could not own that nature in the zealous profeſſing Jews, notwithſtanding they ſeemed to juſtifie themſelves in words to his face, as if they were the children of God, ſaying, <hi>We have one father, even God, Joh.</hi> 8.41. Mark his anſwer and Character of the children of God, <hi>If God were your father, ye would love me.</hi> Love to the truth, Chriſt, the light, is the work of a child of God; hatred to the truth, Chriſt the light, and thoſe that be in it, is the work of a child of the Devil; thus their works makes them manifeſt in all ages: hatred againſt the appearance of God, comes from the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed nature that ſlew the Lamb.</p>
            <p>And to the Profeſſors of the Law of God that were in that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:107025:20"/>his Son ſaid, and doth ſay, <hi>Ye ſeek to kill me:</hi> and what it the reaſon? <hi>becauſe my word hath no place in you.</hi> This is the cauſe of perſecution and enmity againſt the truth, from the firſt to the laſt; the word of truth not being hearkened to, in the heart, in the mouth, truth comes not to be beloved in the inward parts; and by ſuch it comes to be hated in others without: <hi>If ye continue in my word, then art ye my Diſciples indeed.</hi> So mark this, if the word of truth, that which ſpeaks the truth in you hearts, and ſhews your evil deeds in ſecret, and telleth you upon your beds your ſecret faults and wickedneſſe, and makes you confeſſe in your hearts it is ſo, and brings you to a ſenſe of ſorrow and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery that will be your portion, if you repent not and turn to the Lord, that ſpirit that ſearched thy heart, and tried thy reins, that pure word of truth that cannot deceive thee, the annointing that ſpeaks the truth in thee, and this I ſay from the ſpirit of truth, except thou believe in that word of truth, and obey it, thou ſhalt never witneſſe ſalvation. This is the infallible truth to all upon the face of the whole earth, and there is no other ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion under heaven, nor no other Name given, to be ſaved by, then this, <hi>which is the Gentiles light, and Iſraels glory:</hi> that which make manifeſt the deeds of darkneſſe, and reproves them; this is that ſpirit that reproves the world of ſin, that leads out of ſin all that do believe and follow it: and this is he, that ſpirit, that <hi>is given for a leader to his people, to be his ſalvation to the ends of the earth.</hi> This is the Word of God, the Son of God, the <hi>Lamb of God that taketh away the ſin,</hi> and ſaves the ſouls of all that believe in him, the Son, the truth that maketh free; <hi>the quickening ſpirit,</hi> that quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens to life again, the ſoul that was dead in <hi>Adam, and ſo brings Immortality to light, through his power, which is the Goſpel;</hi> and he that believes not in his power, knows not the Goſpel, that power which ſets free from ſin, for that is the <hi>glad tidings to the ſoul,</hi> to hear of a deliverance from the bondage of corruption, that it may no longer ſerve ſin, the wages whereof is condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and death to it; but that it might come to Sow in the eternal ſpirit, and Reap the Wages of life everlaſting: <hi>for ſuch as it ſows, ſuch muſt it reap,</hi> becauſe God is Juſt.</p>
            <p>And therefore they that do believe in the eternal power, have denyed themſelves, and given up their ſouls into the hands of a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:107025:21"/>faithful Creator, that he may ſave them from the ſin, and take it away, and bring in his own perfect righteouſneſſe, according to his promiſe in his New Covenant of free mercy and grace; and it is unpoſſible for God in Chriſt to faile or forſake them, <hi>but keeps Covenant and mercy for ever,</hi> and ſaves the ſoul from the ſin, and power of hell and death, which is the Work his father hath ſent him into the world to do and perform; and he that doth believe in him, he hath promiſed to raiſe him up out of the Fall, Death, and the Curſe, and reſtore him into the life of God (from which he fell, and was dead to) and brings forth a new birth, by creating a new heart, and renewing a right ſpirit in him; and this is his promiſe to do, and work to perform, and ſuch who are not of this Faith, can never have this Work wrought in them; but do, through their unbelief, as it were, make him a lyar; that is, as if he would not, or could not performe his promiſe: <hi>and ſuch are dead while they live,</hi> in the Sinne, Fall, and the Curſe, <hi>Reprobate to every good worke,</hi> diſhonouring the Lord of life, through their unbelief of the truth.</p>
            <p>But on the contrary, believing the lying ſpirit that leads into the ſin, who ſaith that ſin muſt be lived in while we are on the earth, this is the Doctrine of the Devil, and the Devils Doctrine which he hath taught his ſervants and Miniſters to preach, who are the falſe Prophets that daube with untempered morter, that deceive the Nations; ſo upholding the kingdome of the Devil, ſin, and darkneſſe, that he may keep his Kingdome and power in their hearts, and rule there in the diſobedient, and bring forth his will, that is, ſin, and iniquity, and ungodlineſſe, ſo beget his owne Image in them, and do his owne Work through them, and Preach his own Doctrine in them, in which they believing, can never witneſſe ſalvation.</p>
            <p>But are a company of miſerable ſinners, laden with ſin and iniquity, <hi>ever learning of the deceitful lying ſpirit, and ſo can never come to the knowledg of the truth,</hi> that ſets free from ſin, but are ever pleading for it, being in the error ſtrayed from the way of Gods ſalvation, doing the things they ought not to do, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting, hating, and killing the Innocent, ſpoyling and robbing them of their goods, acting in madneſſe and folly beyond the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:107025:21"/>very letter of the law, and ſometimes againſt it; as for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſome are excommunicated, (out of the aſſembly of miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſinners) their Church, ſo called; and after excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion have had their goods ſtrained on, and taken away, for not coming to their worſhip in the time of excommunication; this is unreaſonable, cruel, envious, wicked dealings, and this is done againſt many, caſting others into Dungeons, and naſty holes, and Priſons, that hath deſtroyed their lives, and all becauſe we ſpeak the truth, and do the things that we ought to do, and cannot hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to the lying ſpirit, that leads into errour, and aſtray from the way of God.</p>
            <p>But do hear the voice of Chriſt, the good ſhepherd, and Biſhop of our ſouls, and keep his ſayings, who ſaith, <hi>ſwear not at all, and do not after their works</hi> (who are blind guides) <hi>that ſay, and do not</hi> (the thing they ſay they ought to do) <hi>but believe in the light that ye may be the children of light,</hi> John 12.36. for ſaid he, <hi>I am the light of the world, he that followeth me,</hi> (not blind guides) <hi>ſhall not walk in darkneſſe, but ſhall have the light of life;</hi> chap. 8.12, 13. <hi>then ſaid the Phariſees thy record is not true,</hi> mark what the blind guides ſaid then; and are they not blind guides that ſay ſo now? who ſay, it is but a natural light, <hi>that is the light of the world, that lighteth every man that cometh into the world,</hi> and that it is not able to ſave a man from ſin, though it do condemn him, and reprove him for ſin, and the deeds of darkneſs; when as Chriſt himſelf, the truth that cannot lye, ſaid, <hi>he that followeth him, the light, ſhall not walk in darkneſſe,</hi> and we who are come to the light in our ſelves, and follow it, do bear teſtimony, (againſt all the blind guides, and hireling prieſts, and falſe prophets upon the face of the whole earth) that his record is true: but this the unbelieving Jews could not believe then, no more than the unbelieving Gentiles can believe now, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they walk in darkneſſe, and hate the light; <hi>but this is the word of the Lord God of truth, to all the Gentiles upon the whole earth, they muſt believe in their light, (that is to ſay, the Gentiles light) before ever they can witneſſe Gods ſalvation, for that is his Covenant to the people, and his ſalvation to the ends of the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:107025:22"/>
            <p>What if the blind ſhould ſay, what to do, anſwer, to ſave them from walking in darkneſs, and then the fruits and works of darkneſſe cannot be brought forth? I cannot believe this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, ſaith the blind guide and his followers, then ſaith Chriſt, <hi>for if ye believe not that I am be,</hi> (what he? the true light) <hi>ye ſhall dye in your ſins:</hi> then ſaith Jeſus again unto them, <hi>I go my way, and ye ſhall ſeek me, and ſhall dye in your ſins, whither I go, ye cannot come.</hi> Mark that, ye deſpiſers, and haters of the light, ye deſpiſe and hate Chriſt, and ye that will not follow him the light, here in this world, ſhall not follow him hereafter into the glory of the world to come, but ſhall dye in your ſin, and periſh eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally.</p>
            <p>Conſider this, ye deſpiſers of truth, there is but a breath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt you and eternal deſtruction, ye haters of the light, the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal word, by which you breath, move, and have a being, who plead for ſin, and the deeds of darkneſs, to live in them for tearm of life, read your portion, that live and die in ſin, and conſider what he hath ſaid that cannot lye, if you will not live the life of the righteous, (being manifeſted unto you in the day of viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) you cannot dye the death of the righteous, <hi>nor ſhall your laſt end be like unto his; becauſe he hath called, and you refuſed, he hath ſtretched out his hand (of mercy) and you will not regard; ye have ſet at naught all his counſel, (by his meſſengers he hath ſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you) and would none of his reproof, (by his light in your conſciences, the ſpirit of truth that he hath ſent to reprove the world of ſin,) therefore ſaith he that cannot lye, I will laugh at your calamity, I will mock when your fear cometh, and when diſtreſs and anguiſh cometh upon you: then ſhall you call, but I will not anſwer, you ſhall ſeek him early, but ſhall not find him:</hi> Pro. 1.24, 25, 26, 27. therefore becauſe the ſpirit of truth hath ſaid it, you that are in that capacity, cannot dye the death of the righteous, who ſhall in Gods peace (that he hath laboured after with all men) lye down, <hi>and in his everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting habitation dwell ſafely, and ſhall be quiet from fear of evil, for the upright ſhall dwell in the land, that the envy of</hi> Cains <hi>ſpirit ſhall not, nor cannot baniſh them out of; and the perfect ſhall remain in it.</hi> Theſe be a people, whoſe life the blind guides could never yet ſee in all ages, becauſe they dwelt not in their land, which is the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:107025:22"/>land of darkneſs, where <hi>Cain</hi> ſaid he ſhould be hid from the face of God: therefore all his generation loves this land of darkneſs, naturally, to this day, it being the land of their nativity, where their fathers City is built; (out from the preſence of the Lord, and the bleſſing of the light of his countenance) in that land of the valley of the ſhadow of death, where the ſitting down is in darkneſſe, and the Prince of the power of darkneſſe bears rule there, teaching his children and ſubjects to plead for his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of liberty in the fleſh, which natural deſires and luſts of the fleſh being brought forth, is the life after the fleſh, that cannot pleaſe God; the old mans life in the curſe, in whom the ſeed of the ſerpent, the ſubtileſt beaſt, is head, and makes war in the old enmity againſt the ſeed of the woman, of which is the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, or the birth after the ſpirit, that the birth after the fleſh perſecutes and hates, as <hi>Cain</hi> did, <hi>who was of that wicked one, and ſlew his brother: and wherefore ſlew he him? becauſe his own works were evil, and his brothers righteous:</hi> 1 John 3.12. therefore it is no marvel that the children of light are hated of the world, that lyeth in wickedneſſe, and pleads for it, and hates the light, and pleads againſt it, for he that hateth the light, abides in darkneſſe, and loveth not his brother; and its written, <hi>whoſoever hateth his brother is a murtherer, and ye know that no murtherer hath eternal life abiding in him;</hi> and where eternal life is not abiding, there is <hi>Cains</hi> nature dwelling, and from that nature ariſeth the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor, that doth not well, in doing the things he ought not to do, and ſo fin lyeth at his door. <hi>And woe unto the wicked, it ſhall be ill with him, (ſaith the ſpirit of the Lord) for the reward of his hands ſhall he given him,</hi> Iſaiah 3.11. <hi>For the wicked ſhall be cut off from the earth, and the tranſgreſſors ſhall be rooted out of it,</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs 2.22.</p>
            <p>Therefore let all that have yet a day, prize it, <hi>and make your calling and election ſure,</hi> in this the day of Gods love, and tender viſitation to your ſouls; and think not to ſay in your hearts, did not the thief upon the Croſſe dye the death of the righteous? yes: and did he not live the life of the righteous? yes: he lived by faith, though it might be but the laſt hour, he being then cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led at the laſt hour, to believe in Chriſt the light of the world: he followed him by faith in him, and bore a glorious teſtimony
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:107025:23"/>for him, when moſt of his Diſciples had forſook him, and the blind guides laugh'd him to ſcorn, and wagged their heads at him; then he who was faithful reproved his fellow, that was as blind as his guides and chief prieſts, ſo the prieſts, and the thief, and the elders, were all in one ſpirit of envy, mocking, and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the truth, and choſe the murtherer and the thief (of which ſpirit they were of) before the truth, the ſon of God, which ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit he that believed did rebuke, and that was a good work in that hour, when few durſt own him: but yet more then all this, he confeſſed him to be a king, and that a heavenly one too, before the face of his enemies, and before the whole world, juſtified the righteous ſon of God, and ſaid <hi>he had done nothing amiſſe;</hi> (which proved his enemies the chief prieſts murtherers) and in ſuch a time, when he was in his loweſt eſtate, when he ſaid, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou for ſaken me?</hi> then did he honour him, by his faith, which preached God had not forſaken him, but had given him an everlaſting kingdome, and did not doubt, but he was able to bring his ſoul that believed into his kingdome, therefore ſaid, <hi>Lord, remember me when thou comeſt into thy kingdome,</hi> and ſo received him before the face of the world, as a faithful witneſſe to the death, who entred into the glorious paradice of God, that his precious faith had fitted him for in that ſhort time.</p>
            <p>And if in ſo ſhort a time faith in the power of God can bring forth ſuch a glorious work; what wretched, wicked, miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, unbelieving ſinners are they, who ſay they be in Chriſt the ſon of God, yet do not expect to be ſaved from their ſin, and ſet free from their iniquity, all the dayes of their life? theſe make but a bad confeſſion of the work of faith, which is not to the glory of God the Father, that hath ſent his ſon to take away the ſin, and the work ſtill undone that he came to do; but ſuch are ſtrangers to the true Faith, that a grain of which removes the mountain of ſin and wickedneſſe, <hi>that all the blood of bulls, and of goats, and the aſhes of an heifer, could not remove under the firſt covenant, though that took away the guilt after the ſin committed, yet made nothing perfect (there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he found fault with it, and took it away) but the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in of a better hope did make perfect for ever them that are
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:107025:23"/>ſanctified:</hi> ſo if the ſecond Covenant had not made perfect, as appertaining to the Conſcience, it had been as unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table in that thing as the firſt; but the bringing in of the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hope did, and doth, that which all the children of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe cannot believe, but he that doth believe, <hi>hath this hope, that purifies as he is pure,</hi> and this is the faith that purifies the heart, and overcomes the world in it, <hi>and crucifies the fleſh, with the affections and luſts:</hi> and this is the work of him that God hath ſent into the world, and raiſed him up <hi>to bleſſe all thoſe that believe in his name, in turning away every one of them from his iniquities,</hi> that they may come to abide in him that ſinneth not, that he, whoſoever he be that lives in ſin hath neither ſeen nor known.</p>
            <p>Woe, woe, from the Lord God of power, is the portion of all thoſe that ſay, or have ſaid in their hearts, we will try the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers God, whether he be able to deliver, or ſave them out of our hands, that we ſhould not execute upon them the intents, and inventions of our hearts, in breaking their meetings, and ſcattering them, that they ſhould not be a people; unto all you be it known, from the ſpirit of the Quakers God, your coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel ſhall not ſtand, neither ſhall your decrees proſper; for you have taken it againſt the holy ſeed, that God hath bleſſed, <hi>even againſt the ſeed of</hi> Abraham, <hi>in which all the families of the earth ſhall be bleſſed;</hi> which is the ſeed that could not bow to the pride of <hi>Homan,</hi> againſt whom his ſealed decrees could not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper, but what he prepared againſt them became his own portion: as it is written, <hi>the wicked are ſnared in the works of their own hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And you ſhall know, that the God of the people, ſcornfully called Quakers, is the God of the whole earth, and a God of the mountains, and above the loftineſſe of the hills, as well as the low valleys; and alſo a God of the ſeas, (and above the lofti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the proud waves thereof) as well as of the land; a God infinite in mercy to all that bow to his great and glorious name, and ſubmit to the government of his ſpirit of truth, that is come, and hath revealed it ſelf in our hearts, to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of our ſouls; <hi>unto which every ſoul ought to be ſubject, and ſerve him with reverence and godly fear:</hi> but unto thoſe that deſpiſe his name, and caſt his commands behind their backs, and do deſpight unto his ſpirit of grace, (in labouring to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:107025:24"/>deſtroy the work it hath brought forth, in the little remnant it hath gathered, under its government, who have, and are ſubjecting themſelves unto its pure leadings) unto ſuch, he is a God dreadful in Judgement, terrible in vengeance, to whom it belongs to repay: and as it is written, <hi>Hebrews</hi> 10.31. <hi>It is a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And woe be to all thoſe that are ſtriving againſt their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, and decreeing againſt his decrees, and labouring to ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that which his ſpirit hath gathered, and to deſtroy that which he hath quickened to life, becauſe it cannot ſubmit to a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſpirit, that is of the world, and leads into bondage, which is the voice of the ſtranger that the ſheep of Chriſt cannot follow; but the ſheep muſt hear, and will hear the voice of him that gives eternal life; <hi>who is cowe to ſeek, and to ſave that which was loſt,</hi> and that which was loſt being found and ſaved, will for ever ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour its ſalvation, in preferring the honour and glory of its Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, before all the glory of the world; and for the obedience of his commands, (that his will may be done in earth as in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven) will give up even life, liberty, eſtate, and all, that the world may know the kingdome of God is come, in great pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and glory into our ſouls, when his will is preſerred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our mortal lives, and his commands before liberty and eſtate, that it may preach to the ends of the earth, that we have found ſomething that is better than all things that wicked men can take from us; and becauſe we love and honour that which is from above, that which is from beneath hates us: and becauſe we cannot worſhip and honour it, therefore would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy us: but we ſee him that is inviſible with us, who is high to ſave and deliver us, and will not leave us that have left our ſelves, that he may be received, and who will not deny us that have denyed our ſelves, and our own wills, that his may be done; and where his will is done, his power is come, <hi>and his ſervants we are whom we obey,</hi> and we know our maſter will ſtand by us, while we do his will; and all you that do not know whoſe ſervants we are, (becauſe our manners and beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour is not after the faſhion of this world) you laugh us to ſcorn, like as the old world did at <hi>Noahs</hi> ſalvation, that the Scripture might be fulfilled; <hi>as it was in the dayes of Noah, ſo ſhall it be in the coming of the ſon of man:</hi> you that hate the light can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:107025:24"/>ſee the ſalvation of God, no more than they did in the dayes of <hi>Noah; for the prophecy came not in old time by the will of man, but holy men of God ſpake as they were moved of the holy Ghoſt,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.21. and thoſe who have received the ſpirit of Chriſt, which is the ſpirit of prophecy, cannot but ſpeak good of his name that hath brought ſalvation; <hi>for bleſſed is he that cometh in the name of the Lord,</hi> whom the Lords people will receive and hear, but he that cometh in his own name, cometh by the will of man, and the men that ſtand in their own wills do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him, and hear him, but he that comes in the name of the Lord, ſuch cannot receive him; but he that denies himſelf, and takes up the Croſſe of Chriſt, doth receive and hear the Preacher of the Croſſe, which to him <hi>is the power of God: but to them that periſh it is fooliſhneſſe:</hi> 1. Cor. 1.18. <hi>ſo by that, which the wiſe of the world <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ounts fooliſhneſſe, it pleaſeth the Lord to ſave us that believe:</hi> ſo was it in the dayes of <hi>Noah,</hi> he and his houſhold was ſaved by that which the old world counted fooliſhneſſe; but when the Judgement came, the high mountains of mans wiſdome and imaginations could not ſave them: then they knew and ſaw, that his fooliſhneſſe was better than all their wiſdome; and ſo they came to know that in Judgement to their woe, which they refuſed in mercy for their ſalvation.</p>
            <p>And as it was then, ſo is it now, the wiſdome of men is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived for the Doctrine of ſalvation, and the Doctrine of Gods ſalvation is accounted fooliſhneſſe and deluſion, and caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide as a thing of naught, by the wiſe of this world, who account it not worthy to have a room in their hearts, nor in the Nation; and they that have received in their hearts, who believe and obey it, they have made laws to baniſh out of their Native Countrey: but the time is coming, and very nigh at hand, that you ſhall know in terrible Judgments, that your wiſdome was but fooliſhneſſe, and that which you are labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to exalt, is that which God is appeared to caſt aſide and deſtroy; and that which you are labouring to deſtroy and pull down, is that which God is riſen in ſpirit, in the hearts and ſouls of his people, to ſet up: and now you ſhall certainly know whoſe Counſel ſhall ſtand, and we have told you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, but you would not believe the report of the ſpirit of truth; therefore <hi>the arm of Gods ſalvation is not revealed in
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:107025:25"/>you,</hi> which now he is making bare before you, and all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that you may know you have refuſed his Counſel, and ſlighted the day of your Viſitation, and rejected the ſpirit of truth, that would have gathered you, and the power that would have preſerved you, from the hands of all your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, both within and without, which you ſhall ſee and know, is able to preſerve all thoſe that put their truſt in it, and to deliver them out of the hands of all their enemies, ſo far as it ſhall make for his glory, and the good of our ſouls.</p>
            <p>And if he ſhall farther ſuffer us to be-tried, to the laying down of our lives, for his Name ſake, his will be done; and let our God glorifie himſelf with his own, which way he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth: and if we drink deeper of the cup of ſuffering, it is but the ſame our Lord hath drunk, and the baptiſme he hath been baptized with, but the dreggs thereof ſhall his, and our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies drink for ever. <hi>For ſaith he that lifts up his hand to heaven, and lives for ever, If I whet my glittering ſword, and my hand take bold on Judgment, I will render vengeance to my enemies, and will reward them that hate me, I will make my arrows drunk with bloud, (and my ſword ſhall devoure fleſh) and that with the bloud of the ſlain, and of the Captives, from the beginning of revenges upon the enemy. Rejoyce, O ye Nations, with his people, for he will avenge the blood of his ſervants, and will render vengeance to his adverſaries,</hi> (mark) <hi>and will be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful unto his land, and to his people; therefore bleſſed, bleſſed of the Lord, are you his people, that ſuffer for his name ſake, rejoyce and be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding glad,</hi> Deut. 32.41, 42, 43. <hi>If ye be reproached for the name of Chriſt, happy are ye, for the ſpirit of glory and of God reſteth upon you; on their part he is evil ſpoken of, but on your part he is glorified,</hi> 1 Pet. 4.14.</p>
            <p>And are we called to glorifie our God, then let him have the glory due to his great and glorious name, for this is a high, and glorious, honourable calling, above all the glories of the world: above the glory of Kings, Princes, and Emperours: this is the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wherewith the Son glorifies the Father, and the Father glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies his again: <hi>for he hath given them his word, and the world hath hated them, becauſe they are not of the world, but are ſanctified through the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the truth, which the world hates,</hi> John 17.14.</p>
            <p>And how did the Son glorifie the Father? Was it not in doing his will, and bearing witneſſe to his truth? <hi>And every one that is of the truth heareth his voice;</hi> and becauſe we hear his voice and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:107025:25"/>do his will, in bearing witneſſe to the truth, therefore are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hated, perſecuted and ſpoyled by thoſe that are not of the truth: for he that had the Languages was not of the truth, but ſaid, What is truth? (Mark that) for the Languages gives not the knowledg of the truth; but truth was that which he that had the Languages gave ſentance againſt: And ſo it is now in all thoſe that believe not in the true light that ſhines in their hearts, <hi>which gives the light of the knowledge of the glory of God, in the face of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</hi> All that are in the truth, are in that which was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the many Languages were, which began at <hi>Babel,</hi> and, without coming to the truth, there muſt end; but being ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the truth, ſerves the truth in its place, to manifeſt the confuſion of <hi>Babel</hi> that is in the curſe, taking counſel and not of the Lord, and making themſelves a name in the earth, theſe were ſcattered over the face of the earth.</p>
            <p>But the gathering out of the Confuſion and the Curſe, is in the Name of the Lord, that confounds the Wiſdome and Counſell from beneath, that is earthly, ſenſual, and deviliſh: and the Language is in the Confuſion, cannot lead into the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of God, and the unity in his Spirit: but the word that was in the beginning, leads up to the Father, out of the earth where man was driven, out of the Curſe, out of the Tongues and Languages in the Confuſion, where man was ſcattered, out of the wiſdome from beneath, and ſelfiſh counſel of his own heart, out of the names in the fall and alienation, into the Name which is the power and life of the Son of God, that only knows the Father and reveals him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.27. (and not Tongues and Languages) but the ſpirit and life of Jeſus, that the Father hath ſent into the world to do his will; and where he is received he is the Covenant of light, and promiſe of the father to the Gentiles; to them that receive him (by believing in his light) <hi>he is elect and precious,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.7. <hi>but unto them which be diſobedient</hi> (that is, which believe not) <hi>the ſtone which the builders diſalowed, the ſame is made the head of the corner, and a ſtone of ſtumbling, and a rock of offence,</hi> againſt which many have ſplit themſelves (who were once high and mighty in the earth) by diſalowing, him that made Heaven &amp; Earth to rule and reign in the Conſciences of his people, whom he calls out of darkneſſe into his marvellous Light.</p>
            <p>Who are a Choſen Royall Prieſthood, peculiar to the Lord,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:107025:26"/>that he ſhould act them by his ſpirit, to ſhew forth the praiſes due unto his great and glorious Name? And why ſhould men be ſo unreaſonable as to diſalow the Lord of life (that hath quickened our ſouls) to live in them, and rule in them, and do his Fathers will, which way or how he pleaſeth? <hi>ſeeing we are not our own, to do our own will, but are bought with a price, to do the will of him that hath purchaſed us unto himſelf,</hi> and not to the will of any man in the firſt nature, as in things appertaining to God; for there the elder muſt ſerve the younger, for <hi>Jacob</hi> had the bleſſing: and we cannot ſerve two Maſters, that is to ſay, the Will of God, and the Will of man, when contrary to God; and thus we (who keep in the innocency, and cannot pleaſe men, to diſpleaſe God) are grievous ſufferers, and ſome, even unto death, where many thouſand hearts are made ſad, and many thouſand ſpirits Mourn in ſecret.</p>
            <p>Oh that ever ſuch wickedneſſe ſhould be upon recod to poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that the harmleſſe innocent people of <hi>England</hi> ſhould be baniſhed out of their Country for waiting upon the Lord that hath redeemed their ſouls, and praying to their God that made heaven and earth. What? a people redeemed by the precious blood of the Son of God, impriſoned, and baniſhed, and ſpoyled by their Neighbours and Countrymen, and yet call themſelves Chriſtians? Chriſt never yet owned any ſuch, that impriſon, baniſh, and kill their brethren for worſhipping their heavenly father. And dare any that have any fear of God before their eyes, ſay we are not Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians? if ſo, what Chriſtians are you that baniſh your brethren? Chriſt our elder brother never taught you that practice, nor any of his Apoſtles or Diſciples gave you that example, but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary ſaid and commanded to love one another; for <hi>John</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.10. <hi>In this the children of God are manifeſt, and the children of the devil; whoſoever doth not righteouſneſs, is not of God, neither he that loveth not his brother:</hi> ſo it is manifeſt in whom the envious nature dwelleth, <hi>that ſlew his brother becauſe his own works were evil, and his brothers righteous;</hi> and this is the nature of all perſecuters, and ſuch as baniſh their brethren for righteouſneſs ſake, which you ſee the Scriptures ſaith are not of God. And can any be ſo blind, as not to believe that the Lord will viſit for theſe things, and ſtretch out his hand over the Nation in terrible Judgments, that ſhall overtake all you <hi>that put far away the evil day, and cauſe the ſeat of violence to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:107025:26"/>come near?</hi> and then how will you be able to ſtand in Judgment, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Lord ſhall reward every man according to his works?</hi> and if you ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the ſame things at the hand of the Lord, as we receive from you, would you not think it a ſore judgment? then why cannot you in judgment remember mercy, and think upon the afflictions of <hi>Joſeph?</hi> for though re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>was ſould by his brethren for a bond-man into <hi>Egypt,</hi> yet the Lord was with him, and he became ruler over the whole Land: And though his ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings pleaſed not his brethren, for the which they hated him without a cauſe, yet the Lord loved him and bleſſed him with a double portion.</p>
            <p>And now the Shepherd of Iſrael is leading <hi>Joſeph</hi> like a flock; and doth not his waies and ſayings pleaſe you? what is the matter? is it not becauſe the ways of the Shepherd of Iſrael are not as your ways, therefore his ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are not acceptable, nor his teſtimony believed in the mouths of the <hi>people of his flock, and the ſheep of his paſture.</hi> And wherefore doth not his ways pleaſe you? becauſe you love darkneſs more then light, and the luſts of the fleſh more then the life of righteouſneſs; this is that which is natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral to the fleſh, and therefore no new nor ſtrange thing to us, for we know that ſeed can bring forth no better fruit, and therefore it inherits not the promiſe, for the promiſe is to the ſeed that was, and is diſalowed of men, that is it that is choſen of God and precious; for the believing in, and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of, we are diſalowed and hated, as our brethren were in former a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges (but mark this, ye perſecuters of our age) the hated of men was, and is bleſſed of God. He that was ſould and ſeparated from his brethren, being try'd, was found faithful, upon whoſe head the bleſſing came. <hi>Joſeph</hi> was ſould, and <hi>Jeſus</hi> was ſould; <hi>Joſeph</hi> had rule over <hi>Egypt,</hi> and <hi>Jeſus</hi> over the World, <hi>who is become the head of the corner, and ſhepherd of the ſoul, and leads Joſeph like a flock, who is the glory of Iſrael that ſhines forth for our ſalvation,</hi> and bleſſed are they that walk in his light: which is the way that pleaſeth not the world, that lieth in wickedneſſe, &amp; loves their evil deeds, but is the way that pleaſeth the Lord, which he hath bleſſed with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting bleſſing, that it ſhould proſper for ever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ones do walk, and the redeemed of the Lord out of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>For the Lord our God is one, and his way is one, who hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>be one ſold, and one ſhepherd, out of whoſe hand his ſheep ſhall not be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Job. 10.16. Into whoſe Fold we witneſſe a gathering (bleſſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that hath gathered us) and by his eternal ſpirit of life hath quicke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> into a bleſſed hope, that nothing ſhall be able to reanove us, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in this faith. And therefore <hi>what if the Heathen rage, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> a vain thing, and the Kings of the eart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> themſelves<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:107025:27"/>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Lord and his Anointed.</hi> And what if the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> blow, and the ſtorms (o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the wicked) bear, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>odly ſwel, and death and hell combin'd and take counſel together againſt us, yet ſaith he that lives for ever, <hi>I have ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> my King upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of Sion,</hi> and bleſſed are all thoſe whoſe ſouls are ſubject to his Law, that he hath with in their hearts, &amp; to his ſpirit in their inward parts; for it is the law of the ſpirit of life, that the law of the ſpirit of ſtrife &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy ſhall never prevail againſt though it may be formed and new moulded, yet it ſhall no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> proſper, nor accompliſh the end of thoſe that made it.</p>
            <p>And therefore, is there not a cauſe to take up this my limentation over you O ye Rulers and Magiſtrates of <hi>England?</hi> why will you die, O ye peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the paths that lead to deſtuction, when the Lord ſtretcheth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ch his kind of mercy to receive you into his covenant of life? why will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> chuſe your own way, and deſpiſe the path of peace and reſt to yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ls? and why do you diſda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the noble immortal ſeed, that the father or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſown for your ſalvation, that, of which except you be born again, your ſouls periſh for ever? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> do you flight the leadings and te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpirit of truth in the inward parts (which is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> up teachers to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſelves conformable to your own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>able to your wills <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> deceive your ſouls, and one day you ſhall know that theſe things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and that you have hated and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted your beſt friends, even dear friends to your ſouls; who are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> willing to lay, down <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> a teſtimony to that truth, by which your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>And the Lord is our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in his truth, that we deſire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> deſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion of any, neither in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> but the good of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> our enemies might come <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> be f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ed.</hi> And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> prayer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> may not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> day of viſitation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that belong to their everlaſting peace be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to deſtruction for ever. And it is not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that I have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſoul. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> on in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> leads <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that the ſpirit of love and life preſſeth to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and reprove the evil practice, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> O ye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, but a ſufferes by your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>M. W.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:107025:27"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
